<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The stil-destroyer or, Self-seeking discovered. Together with the curse it brings, and the cure it requires. A sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Lord Maior and Court of Aldermen of the city of London, upon occasion of a solemne anniversary meeting, April 9th 1645. / By William Ienkyn Master of Arts, and minister of Gods word at Christ-Church London.</title>
            <author>Jenkyn, William, 1613-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87567</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J655</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E277_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200004</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860806</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860806</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112931</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87567)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112931)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 46:E277[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The stil-destroyer or, Self-seeking discovered. Together with the curse it brings, and the cure it requires. A sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Lord Maior and Court of Aldermen of the city of London, upon occasion of a solemne anniversary meeting, April 9th 1645. / By William Ienkyn Master of Arts, and minister of Gods word at Christ-Church London.</title>
                  <author>Jenkyn, William, 1613-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Christopher Meredith at the Crane in Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 25".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Philippians II, 20-21 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112931:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112931:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Stil-Destroyer OR, Self-ſeeking Diſcovered.</p>
            <p>Together With the Curſe it brings, and The Cure it requires.</p>
            <p>A SERMON Preached BEFORE THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE THE LORD MAIOR and Court of Aldermen of the City of LONDON, upon occaſion of a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Anniverſary meeting, <hi>April</hi> 9<hi rend="sup">th,</hi> 1645.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM IENKYN Maſter of Arts, and Miniſter of Gods Word at Chriſt-Church LONDON.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Serpit putrida tabes hypocrifis per omne corpus Eccleſiae, et quo lativs co deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratius, eo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> periculofius quo interius. Omnes ſunt amici et omnes inimici, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes neceſſarii, et omnes adverſarii, omnes domeſtici et nulli pacifici, omnes proximi et omnes ferc quae ſua ſunt quaerunt, non quae Jeſu Chriſti.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 38.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>*Sic <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulg. <hi>Ecce in pace amaritudo mea.</hi> Amara pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in nece marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion, amarior poſt in conflictu haereticorum, amariſſima nunc in moribus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticorion.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Bern. Serm. 33. in Cantic.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſid. Peluſ. Lib. 5. Ep. 498.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Chriſtopher Meredith</hi> at the Crane in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:112931:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112931:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE the Lord MAYOR, and Court <hi>of</hi> ALDERMEN, <hi>of the famous</hi> Citie of LONDON.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He occaſion was ſolemne up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which this Sermon was preach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, the age is cenſorious in which 'tis printed; that did not make me forward to be in the Pulpit; this made me backward to be in the Preſſe: But the concealing of my Sermon would have been the diſcovering of my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, and I rather chuſe to be in Print then in ſuch an oppoſition.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:112931:3"/>
            <p>The ſeaſon is ſtormie wherein my name puts forth, and who obſerves not Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracks in the Seas of this my paſſage, enough to make the ſufferers pitied, and the ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors warned? For my ſelfe, the wiſdome of your Commands is embarqued in the ſame bottom with my name; you make by far the greater adventure, and ſhould there prove a miſcarriage, your loſſe cannot be inferiour: But why ſpeak I of ſtorms or loſſes? may my veſſell but ſet <hi>Chriſt</hi> on ſhore, upon any ſoul, it matters not afterward what becomes of it or me. My aime was ſervice, not ſafetie, I went not out upon pleaſure, but employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Sermons are but <hi>Machinae,</hi> ſcaffolds to ſet up <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the heart; they obtaine their end in the furtherance of his work, not in the firmneſs of their owne ſtanding. Our conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing longer then'till <hi>Chriſt</hi> be erected, is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on favour, not neceſsitie.</p>
            <p>The way whereby I deſire in this Sermon the advancing of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is principally I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe by deſtroying of that enemy which both hinders the ſetting of <hi>Chriſt</hi> up, and if let alone, will alſo cauſe our downefall; for the
<pb facs="tcp:112931:3"/>ſin I here ſtrike at, is very improperly called <hi>ſelf-ſeeking,</hi> he who is uſually termed a <hi>ſelf-ſeeker,</hi> neither attending upon that which is truely <hi>ſelf,</hi> nor upon the right <hi>ſeeking</hi> of it. That cannot be ſaid to be done for <hi>ſelf,</hi> which is not done for the <hi>ſoule,</hi> whatſoever is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe done being for <hi>luſts,</hi> or at the beſt for the moth, the theefe, the carkaſſe, rather then for ones <hi>ſelf.</hi> The <hi>ſoule-ſeeker</hi> is the true <hi>ſelf-ſeeker.</hi> Nor can this attending upon <hi>ſelf</hi> be called a <hi>ſeeking,</hi> unles by it we underſtand a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious painful toyling, and in that ſenſe eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>ſinner</hi> is a true <hi>ſeeker,</hi> but in reſpect of any wiſe diſpoſall, or right ordering of endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours toward the thing principally deſired, which is good &amp; happines, it may more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be termed <hi>a loſing then a ſeeking;</hi> rather a going from, then toward the thing after which there is made a ſeeming enquirie. <hi>To ſeeke our ſelves by</hi> ſinning, by diſtruſting Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, by exceſsivenes in earthly induſtries, by deſerting the Cauſe of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> eſpecially by driving our owne unworthy <hi>deſignes</hi> under pretence of friendſhip to the <hi>Church,</hi> this kind
<pb facs="tcp:112931:4"/>of <hi>ſelf-ſeeking</hi> is <hi>in Scripture politiks</hi> no better then <hi>ſelfe-loſing.</hi> This is the enemy againſt whom I bend the force of this enſuing Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; wherein if I ſee me to charge him with too much adventurouſneſs, let the hurtfulnes both of his nature and practiſe be my excuſe; for though it would be moſt happy living when <hi>ſelf-ſeeking</hi> were dead, ye who would not with <hi>Sampſon</hi> even willingly die, ſo as but this one <hi>Philiſtine</hi> might bee killed alſo? God hath followed this <hi>Sermon</hi> with two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Preach'd of late by the <hi>mouth of the ſword,</hi> in the very <hi>bowels</hi> of this Kingdome; The one was a puniſhment upon <hi>ſelf-ſeeking</hi> by our loſſe of a<note n="*" place="margin">L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iceſter.</note> Towne, the other a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon <hi>ſeeking him</hi> by our winning the<note n="*" place="margin">In that glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous victor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e at Naſiby.</note> Field; In the firſt hee taught us this leſſon, <hi>ſeeking our ſelves and not God ruines us.</hi> In the ſecond, this; <hi>Seeking God and not our ſelves revives us;</hi> Oh that hee would pleaſe to Preach once more, and that by the <hi>Sword of his mouth,</hi> the power of his owne Spirit; for otherwiſe, 'tis poſsible indeed to ſcatter Armies and overcome Cities,<note place="margin">Pro. 16.32.</note> but never will
<pb facs="tcp:112931:4"/>this <hi>Spirituall and Beloved enemy ſelf</hi> be vanquiſhed; However, I have labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to diſcharge my truſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to quice my Conſcience in diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Deſtroyer. The Lord grant that <hi>England</hi> may voyce him, and think him to bee as that people did <hi>Sampſon,</hi> when hee was brought before them, the <hi>Enemy and Deſtroyer of their Countrey and Kingdome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 16.24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In particular, I knew not better how to expreſſe my deareſt reſpects to this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous City, whoſe <hi>Lord Mayor,</hi> with ſundry of her <hi>Aldermen</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> have been formerly pleaſed to aſsiſt my now <hi>dear charge,</hi> in calling mee to the place of my preſent <hi>Miniſtery:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this former love to my ſelf, that of late to my plaine dealing, (more then which, I know nothing, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured your approbation to this Sermon) deſerves a larger expreſsion in this kind, of my gratefull reſenting your religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous favours; However, this teſtimony, ſuch as it is, of my deſires to ſerve your
<pb facs="tcp:112931:5"/>ſouls, I humbly preſent to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable acceptance, beſeeching God that <hi>Chriſt-ſeeking,</hi> and not <hi>Self-ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> may ever be your Honor, and <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons</hi> happineſſe, as a Miniſter wherein I am even to humbleſt acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your ſervant for Ieſus ſake,</hi> William Ienkyn.</signed>
               <dateline>Chriſt-Church, <hi>London.</hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112931:5"/>
            <head>THE STIL-DESTROYER DISCOVERED.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 PHILIPPIANS 20.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For I have no man like minded, who will naturally care for your ſtate.</p>
                  <p>For all ſeeke their owne, not the things of <hi>IESVS CHRIST.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T the writing whereof the body of <hi>Paul</hi> was under the reſtraint of bonds and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, but never was the ſoule of this bleſſed man more then at this time enlarged; his ſoule was happy in a double enlargement. Firſt, in that <hi>of ſpirituall ioy,</hi> ſecondly, <hi>of ſpirituall deſire. His ioyes</hi> were ſo abundant, that hee expreſſeth them neare twentie ſeverall times in this no long Epiſtle; never made he ſo frequent mention <hi>of death, bonds and diſſolution,</hi> as in this Epiſtle, nor ever made he more frequent expreſſions of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine joyes and comforts; now he exhorteth the <hi>Philippians (for he had of this oyle of ioy for their lamps alſo)</hi> to rejoyce,<note place="margin">Chap. 3.1.4.</note> to rejoyce alway, and againe to rejoyce; The thorne was at his breaſt, and never ſang he ſo ſweetly as now;<note place="margin">Chap. 4.4.</note> He had a fountaine of joy in his ſoule, which the ſcorching ſeaſon of a priſon was not able to dry
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112931:6"/>up; Oh the power and effic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cie of <hi>the ſupplies of the Spirit of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 1.19.</note> How able are they to poſe the cruelties of men? There is ſtill as much <hi>in Ieſus Chriſt</hi> for us; his comforts are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, not impaired; a priſon cannot keepe him more out now then in <hi>Pauls</hi> time. He ſtill loves to feed his people through the grate, and when hee ſends them a great journey of trouble and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>derling, to bid them once and againe, <hi>up and eat:</hi> and will the Lord keepe us from <hi>ſoul-ſtraitnings?</hi> what matters it how ſtrict and cloſe the confinements of our bodies are?</p>
            <p>For the largeneſſe of <hi>Pauls deſires,</hi> they were not in <hi>this Epiſtle</hi> employed for him ſelfe as priſoners wiſhes commonly are, but for <hi>the Philippians.</hi> His own miſeries loſe themſeves in the fears of theirs; his only griefe was that <hi>of compaſſion;</hi> throughout all this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing <hi>Epiſtle</hi> I find him <hi>weeping</hi> but once,<note place="margin">Chap. 3.18.</note> and that was from ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of their dangers.<note place="margin">Chap. 1.23.</note> His deſire of benefiting their ſouls could have made him content at one time almoſt,<note place="margin">Si dives quiſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulieri pauper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulae dicat, Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere tu ad pran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um, ſed quem geſtas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantulum relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que for is, quoui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> plorat et moleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us eſt nobis, nunquid faciet? nonne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis eliget jejuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, quam expoſito pignore charo ſola prandere cum divite? ita, &amp;c. <hi>Bern. Serm. 12. in Cant. Verſe 19.</hi>
               </note> to ſtay a while longer from <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and (as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeakes of another) ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſtand at the dore a begging with his children in the raine, then to goe in and feaſt <hi>with Ieſus Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, and leave them without. Oh the excellency of a publique Spirit! Tis not limited or confined within the bounds of <hi>ſelfe concernments.</hi> Oh the greatneſſe of a Soule widened, with deſires to advance the Kingdome of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt! Pauls</hi> zeale in this reſpect puts him upon contriving ſome way of making a ſupply of his neceſſitated abſence from the <hi>Philippians;</hi> what he could not doe by himſelfe, he deſires to doe by another, even <hi>Timothie,</hi> him hee promiſeth to ſend as a <hi>living Epiſtle</hi> to ſecond this other, ſo as <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> might be advanced, hee cares not by whom it were, whether by himſelfe or another. He was willing to ſtand in the crowd and be hidden, ſo as <hi>Chriſt</hi> might ſtand upon his ſhoulders and be ſeen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> being about to give a<note n="*" place="margin">Omnes has vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes de Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theo praedicat ut majori <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>routla cum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>entom ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ane. in loc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Commiſſion to Timothie</hi> for this purpoſe, ſends firſt <hi>a commendation of him.</hi> Hee commends him from his <hi>carefulneſſe</hi> of the <hi>Philippiuns ſtate.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from his holy ſolicitouſnes, the word importeth a ſoul-cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting care. 'Tis then happy with the Church of God, when they who are employ'd in it, have endowments ſutable to their em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, eſpecially that of caring for ſoules. <hi>Miniſters</hi> muſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112931:6"/>not then bee without care when they are to enter upon it. How unfitly are many Congregations in this diſtracted <hi>England</hi> called Cures? many there are that cut the ſoules of their people, few that cut their owne ſoules with caring for their people; <hi>Timothie</hi> had within him a ſoul-diving care for the <hi>Philippians ſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This care in <hi>Timothie</hi> toward the <hi>Philippians, Paul</hi> commends for its <hi>ſincerity,</hi> its <hi>naturalnes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> He careth for your ſtate naturally (ſaith he) that is, <hi>heartily, truely, not paintedly, appearingly, artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Non neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis vinculo, ſed voluntatis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quio.</note> or (as ſome) willingly, not conſtrainedly; <hi>Timothie</hi> was not a Miniſter in title, in dignitie, in coat, in cloth, but in truth; hee had <hi>the heart of a Miniſter in him;</hi> hee was not a <hi>Praelate in ſhew, and a Pilate in heart, as</hi> Bernard <hi>complaines</hi> of ſome in his time;<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> there was in him <hi>Genuinus germanus affectus,</hi> a reality of inward and hearty affection toward the <hi>Philippians;</hi> he was carefull <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally,</hi> ſincerely.</p>
            <p>This <hi>ſinceritie</hi> of <hi>Timothies</hi> care <hi>Paul</hi> commends from the <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie</hi> of it; I have none, faith hee, <hi>like-minded, equally-hearted to Timothie</hi> in this cauſe of Chriſt, I have divers Miniſters with me,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but onely one <hi>Timothy,</hi> the reſt are far inferiour to him in integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and of a lower forme in Miniſteriall fitnes to be employed, hee is the moſt choicely ſpirited man that I know in all<note n="*" place="margin">If <hi>Peter</hi> were now at <hi>Rome,</hi> the Papiſts have little cauſe to boaſt of him, rather how doe they diſgrace him, in ſaying was ſo? <hi>O triſte et f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> dum Elog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. in. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Rome;</hi> I have not his fellow left when hee is gone, <hi>Paul</hi> had no regard to his owne private loſſe of ſo precious a companion; he had but one, and he too was deſerving, and receiving from <hi>Paul</hi> the love of a father, yet part with him he will if the Church want him. O ſelf-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſoul! how doſt thou ſhame thoſe, who boaſting that they suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in the place of <hi>Apoſtleſhip,</hi> are (were at leaſt) yet ſo farre from the grace of it, that if <hi>Philippi</hi> had beene in their Dioces, would rather have taken away from <hi>Philippi</hi> an hundred <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies</hi> and not have left one, then have ſent one to <hi>Philippi,</hi> though there had beene a hundred by them deſirous to goe? 2. <hi>Paul</hi> to make the <hi>Philippians</hi> value <hi>Timothie</hi> the more, tels them that ſuch <hi>Timothies</hi> were very rare a motive likely to be prevalent to move reſpect to <hi>Timothie.</hi> The rarity of godly Miniſter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> height en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the eſteeme of them. Oh that the times wherein were live were not too ſad a proof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hereof! When our <hi>Timothies</hi> were rare how fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently were they beloved? but now they are by the bleſſing of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112931:7"/>God in greater abundance (in theſe parts) how commonly are they loathed? And this is occaſioned by the plentie of their labours, under which coſt of a good God we grow more luxuriant and rank in weeds, more propenſe to libertie, pride, contentions, and contempt of Gods ſo familiar Diſpenſations, even to the taking up the old trade new dreſt; I meane a ſiner ſpunne perſecution. Take heed, if raritie be a meanes to procure love to Miniſters, the Lord may ſoon remove from you theſe now (as they are counted) <hi>Antichriſtian burdens,</hi> and by their <hi>raritie</hi> teach you to eſteeme them; I ſcare your madneſſe muſt be cured by keeping you in the dark, and that with ſhorter and courſer fare too. <hi>Paul</hi> endeavours to heighten the <hi>Philippians</hi> eſteeme of <hi>Timothy,</hi> by declaring the unuſualneſs of ſuch <hi>Timothies; I have none equally minded, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> gives the reaſon of this raritie in the 21. <hi>verſ.</hi> the words that I chuſe in my following diſcourſe to inſiſt upon; What is the cauſe that there are few or none beſides <hi>Timothie</hi> that regard the <hi>things, the ſtate of the Church?</hi> becauſe others <hi>ſeek their own things,</hi> therefore not <hi>Chriſts things.</hi> Their affections are full flood <hi>earth-ward, ſelfe-ward;</hi> therefore ebbing <hi>heaven-ward, Chriſt-ward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>All ſeek</hi>] He ſpeakes not of thoſe that had made an open de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection from the faith, totally forſaking the Apoſtle, as <hi>Hymeneus, Philetus, &amp;c.</hi> but of thoſe who were <hi>Brethren and fellow labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers:</hi> Nor yet doth hee intend that ſimply all theſe were ſo neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lective of the things of Chriſt, as that there was not one but <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie</hi> that regarded the Church; for there was <hi>Epaphr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ditus</hi> and others who did regard them, but the word <hi>[All]</hi> is here to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as elſ-where, &amp; in common ſpeech it is uſed, that is, not as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting its full extent, and as it is moſt comprehenſive, but as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting the generalitie, the many, the moſt; ſo when <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes as if all the <hi>Cretians</hi> were evill beaſts and ſlow bellies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit. 1.12.13. So we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay,</hi> Nuſquem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uta ſides<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> caſtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in Italia Om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es in Hispa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia ſuperbi.</note> he muſt be underſtood as ſpeaking of the moſt; the <hi>generalitie</hi> of the fault, cauſing an expreſſion <hi>of univerſalitie.</hi> All, almoſt, or for the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralitie ſeek their owne things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seek</hi>] The word ſignifieth an eager and ſtudious <hi>proſecution and deſire,</hi> by way of <hi>enquirie</hi> after any thing; (as <hi>Mark</hi> 12.12. <hi>Luke</hi> 11.18.) ſometimes alſo the requiring or exacting of a thing; (<hi>Luk.</hi> 12.46.) here 'tis taken in the former ſenſe, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rts a too <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ager immoderate proſecution of our own things, not a lawfull ſubordinate endeavour to preſerve our ſelves and ours, ſo
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112931:7"/>as to advance Gods glory thereby, but an <hi>immeaſurable vehement out-going of affection after our own things which we make our aime, and end, and ſcope in a way of oppoſitneſſe even to the things of Chriſt himſelf when both come in competition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Their own</hi>] Or things for themſelves, and that belong to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and here they are to be underſtodd of bodily comforts, as riches, health, pleaſures, &amp;c.<note place="margin">Luk. 19.12.</note> though <hi>Chriſt</hi> cals theſe <hi>anothers (Luk.</hi> 16.12.) &amp; thoſe onely <hi>our own</hi> which are our ſouls, Grace being the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>your own,</hi> ſpoken of in that place, and indeed ſpirituall bleſſings onely deſerve this title of <hi>our own,</hi> becauſe they are onely qualified for that part of a man, that is the man, the ſoule, and they onely continue. Other things, the own things ſpoken of here being rather our <hi>Carcaſſes</hi> then <hi>our own,</hi> &amp; they ſhall have others to own them ere long; but in regard of our civill propriety in them among men, and in regard of the <hi>opinions of carnally minded men,</hi> uſing and deſiring them as if their ſouls could be ſatisfied with them, as alſo <hi>own</hi> them always, theſe folicitouſly immoderately regarded things are called <hi>our own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Not the things of Ieſus Chriſt</hi>] What he had called <hi>the ſtate and things of the Church</hi> in the fore-going verſe, he here calls the <hi>things of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> in regard that <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath a true intereſt in the <hi>Church</hi> and all that belongs to it. The Church is his Church,<note place="margin">Eſa. 63.19. John 10.3. Eph. 5.17.</note> her grace, glory, conditions, all his.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Not</hi>] That is, Comparatively to <hi>Timothy;</hi> they were not <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually hearted</hi> to him for the Church, not that they did ſimply throw off all care of the <hi>Church;</hi> but their owne private proper profits and intereſts did ſo take them up, that they had not at that time hearts ſuited to ſo difficult an imployment for Chriſt; <hi>To ſeek the things of Chriſt is to make the glory of Chriſt principally in our ay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es,</hi> to employ our parts and endeavours chiefly for advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing his Honour, <hi>preferring him</hi> to all our private conveniences, or exigences, to make Chriſt the ſcope of our life: ſo <hi>Phi.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">Phil. 1.21.</note> To me to live is Chriſt. Contrarily, not to <hi>ſeek him</hi> is not onely not to regard him <hi>at all,</hi> and <hi>purely</hi> to throw off all looking after the <hi>things of Chriſt,</hi> but not to <hi>ſeek them in the firſt place, and not to propound them as our chiefe end, but rather to undertake employments ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly for Chriſt, but intending principally our own benefit, honour, caſe, &amp;c. more then the things of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:112931:8"/>
            <p>The words of both the verſes thus opened, thoſe of the twenty firſt verſe, which I ſhall onely inſiſt upon containe a proof, and an aggravation of a fault more lightly touched in the foregoing verſe, by occaſion of <hi>Timothies</hi> commendation: The fault was <hi>Carele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of the <hi>Churches ſtate;</hi> the Apoſtle amplifieth it here th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e wayes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by ſhe wing what it was to be careleſſe of the ſtate of the <hi>Church;</hi> t'was to neglect the things even of <hi>Chriſt himſelf: it is a conſiderable perſon that is neglected with the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, by ſhe wing how or upon what ground theſe things of the Church came to be neglected; it was by reaſon of the <hi>ſeeking their own things, it was a very inconſiderable ground upon which they were ſo careles of the things of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, by ſhe wing the <hi>generality</hi> of thoſe that were ſo careles and neglective of theſe things. <hi>All,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> in a manner <hi>all, by f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r the moſt ſeek their own things, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or we may obſerve two things mainly conſiderable in this o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and twentieth verſe,<note place="margin">Diviſion of the words.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, a fault or offence deſcribed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the generablitie of the delinquents or offenders.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Part.</hi>
               </note> the fault hath two branches: Firſt, a poſitive branch, They ſought <hi>their own things.</hi> Secondly, a negative branch, <hi>not the things of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt, the poſitive, firſt, here is <hi>an act</hi> ſeeking, <hi>there is eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>an obiect, their own things, there is unworthineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond the negative branch; there is firſt, the kinde of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffence, it was an omiſſion; the ſtate of the Church was <hi>neglected, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>itted, not the, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gree of it, or the aggravating and heightning of it, <hi>the things o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s of Ieſus Chriſt were neglected in the neglect of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the cauſe of all this neglect neceſſarily implyed, <hi>it was in regard of</hi> following inordinately their own things.</p>
            <p>The generality of the offenders is to be handled under ſeverall conſiderations.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Part.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>In proſecution of this ſecond diviſion ſundry fruitfull obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in every <hi>branch</hi> would offer themſelves,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Part.</hi>
               </note> as, from the firſt part
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112931:8"/>the <hi>offence</hi> as conſidered, firſt, in the poſitive branch,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Branch of the <hi>1.</hi> Part.</note> 
               <hi>the ſeking their owne things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, obſerve as this eager act of ſeeking was beſtowed upon things that were <hi>licita non inhoneſta,</hi> owne things permitted by God to be ſought after, that <hi>wee are very liable to offend in lawfull things.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obſervation.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, as theſe things were <hi>privata non publica,</hi> their own private, not the Publike things,<note place="margin">Obſer.</note> that <hi>it is a very ignoble temper of ſoule for Chriſtians in times wherein the Publike wants them, to regard immoderately their owne private affairs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, as theſe things were <hi>diſſimulata non manifeſta,</hi> things ſought underhand; no man profeſſing or ſeeming to ſeek his own things, but the contrary the good of the Church;<note place="margin">Obſer.</note> that <hi>it is ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but very diſcommendable for Chriſtians, under pretence of ſeeking the things of the Church, to regard mainly themſelves and their own things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So from the offence conſidered in the negative branch, <hi>not the things of Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> firſt, from the kinde of this offence,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Branch of</hi> 2. <hi>Part.</hi>
               </note> it being an offence of omiſſion, we might <hi>obſerve that it is a ſin not onely to perſecute the Church, but even not to labour the proſperity of it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obſer.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, from the aggravation of this neglect of the Church, it being a neglect of the things of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> we might obſerve;<note place="margin">Obſer.</note> firſt, the <hi>propriety and intereſt that Chriſt hath in his Church, and the things of it, they are the things of Chriſt himſelf; as the Church it ſelf, ſo her Grace, Glory, Conditions, Officers, are all his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that this intereſt which Chriſt hath in his Church, and the things thereof, doth much heighten the offence of neglecting the Church, in regard it imports, firſt, <hi>a neglect of a ſervice wee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to advance,</hi> all making a ſhew of ſerving Chriſt.<note place="margin">Obſer.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>a neglect of a ſervice that deſerves our regard by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of its honour, ſafety, ſweetneſſe, advantage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Aneglecting of him that was ſo loving and induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in ſeeking of us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>A neglecting of his ſervice who will one day call us to an account for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, from the cauſe of this neglecting the things of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Obſer.</note> it is obſervable that <hi>the ſeeking our owne things, binders the ſeeking of the things of Chriſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:112931:9"/>
            <p>The ſecond part of the Text, viz. the generalitie of the offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, contains a threefold reſpect.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Part.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Obſer.</note> to <hi>Paul,</hi> in whom it notes ſorrowfull reſentment of this fault, and courage in reproving it.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Obſer.</note> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> by whom it notes commendableneſſe in differing from the generality.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">Obſer.</note> to the ſelf-ſeekers; who were brethren and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labourers; in whom it notes the diſcovery that difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties make of pretenders to Chriſt and his things.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall in this firſt part onely proſecute the laſt particular in the ſecond branch, viz. <hi>the cauſe of the neglect of the things of Chriſt,</hi> and in that the forenamed point which the context compared with the words themſelves, clearly ſhew us was the Apoſtles ſcope; all the other particulars before mentioned in a manner naturally fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in with it in the through handling of it; It was this, <hi>The ſeeking of our owne things will hinder us from ſeeking the things of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Propoſition.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In the proſecution of which point I ſhall proceed, Firſt by way of Explication.</p>
            <p>Secondly, of Confirmation.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, of Application.</p>
            <p>There are three things which want Explication.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Firſt, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition explai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, by ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what kinde of ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is that hinders the ſeeking of the things of Ieſus Chriſt.</note> what kinde of ſeeking our own things it is that will hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us from ſeeking the things of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, what things of Chriſt they are that will be hindered by ſeeking our own things.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, wherein the hinderance ſtands and doth conſiſt, that will follow this ſeeking our own things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What I meane by ſeeking our own things.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What by the things of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What by the hinderance or neglect of the things of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, what I meane <hi>by ſeeking</hi> our owne things. All kinde of ſeeking <hi>our owne things</hi> will not hinder us from <hi>ſeeking the things of Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cura, di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igenti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> There is a <hi>lawfull</hi> and an allowed <hi>ſeeking our owne things;</hi> A diligent, Chriſtian, providentiall labour in looking after them,<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 3.10. 2 Cor. 12.14. 1 Tim. 5.8.</note> is by the Scripture commanded and commeuded, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no repugnancie at all betweene it and ſeeking <hi>the things of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112931:9"/>Chriſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aliqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>do quarere quae ſua ſunt, non pugnat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um illo quod eſt quaerere quae ſunt Ieſu Chriſti. Quarenda quae ſunt Chriſti ſed non negligenda quae ſunt neſtra, <hi>Zanc. in loc.</hi> Nimiam ſolict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem probi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, operationem jubet. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </note> A Chriſtian is not exempted from all kind of ſocking <hi>their owne things,</hi> which as they are to be ſought for from God, before we labour for them upon the earth; ſo muſt wee labour for them upon the earth, when we have ſought them from God; Are wee hungry? we muſt not ſit ſtill till miraculous ſhowres of <hi>Manna</hi> raine downe upon us; Are we thirſtie? we muſt not wait for God to cleave the Rockes into Cups, and give us water thence; Are we deſirous of c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oathing? we doſerve to go naked if we will ſtay till the Sheepe reſigne their coats to be our garments; What then? what kind of ſeeking is it that a Chriſtian muſt ſhun as hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering from ſeeking <hi>the things of Ieſus Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, it is <hi>a ſeeking our owne things with an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iety of heart,</hi> with diſtruſtfulneſſe of Gods promiſe and providence; ſuch <hi>a ſeeking</hi> as wherein we depend not upon a father to ſeeke with us and for us, and to be carefull of us. When we caſt not the burdenſomeneſſe of our ſeeking upon God, when wee are not like the ſheepe that followes the Shepheard for food, but like the Lion alway roaring and raving, as if there were none to provide for us; when as we are <hi>cutting</hi> our <hi>ſoules with care;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 6.25. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Luk. 12.29. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Ne in acre va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamini <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onibus veſtris.</hi> Piſc. Hoſea 12.8. Calv. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mines applandunt ſibi.</hi> Mar. 10.24. Iob. 31.24. Pſal. 52.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> when we are alway of a <hi>doub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>full</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oubled <hi>minde</hi> for theſe own things, as Chriſt ſpeakes; when we hang in ſuſpence for the event of our enquiries, and are like Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teors in the aire toſſed up and downe, hîther and thither, at the pleaſure of every blaſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the ſeeking our owne things <hi>with the beight of raiſed expectation</hi> to ſinde comfort and ſupplies and ſufficiencie in them, hinders from ſeeking the <hi>things of Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> when wee thinke of our <hi>owne things</hi> above what they are; when wee regard our health, wealth, honour, &amp;c. as if there were no other heaven but theſe, and no other hel but the contrary; when we bleſſe our ſelves ſecurely in the hopes or poſſeſſions of them, and <hi>truſt and confide in</hi> them, as Chriſt ſpeakes, <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.24. <hi>Making gold our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, truſting in the abundance of riches.</hi> lí a man thinketh theſe things to be ſomething, when they are nothing, he deceiveth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; they all ſay to a man they are not the things wee lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke for, they point to God; if wee regard them with the height of hopes, and firmneſs of dependencies, wee ſhall neglect all of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the ſeeking our owne things with <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112931:10"/>eagerneſſe</hi> in going out after them, when <hi>the heare i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for upon them,</hi> and ſold unto them, there being no moder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion to held the raines of our induſtrie, wee being carried not with the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tle gales of indifferencie, but the furious winder of vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dence; this kind of ſeeking alſo hinders from <hi>ſeeking the things of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tantum ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> eſt qr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ntum ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ig it natura in ſuo genere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervandae m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dus. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </note> when wee doe not exevciſe our limbes, but cra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> out ſinewes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them, not dip the tip of our rod in taſting the honey o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> profit, ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, honour, &amp;c. but thruſt it in even all over, and engulph and ſwallow up our ſelves in matters of <hi>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond what is enough for our calling and condition; reſolving to have theſe things, what even they coſt us; as the Apoſtle ſpeaks of ſome,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.9.</note> 
               <hi>who will berich;</hi> who will through five and water, and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties; armies of theſe ſhall not hinder them from the water af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which they thirſt.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>The ſeeking our own things unleaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nably,</hi> baſtowing houres upon them that are due to other things, is a ſeeking which makes us neglect <hi>the things of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> when weroh the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of her opportunities, pil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er from God, clip the Sabbath, our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, Religion, the Church and Cauſe <hi>of Chriſt;</hi> when the ſenlofeth here,<note place="margin">2 Kings 5.26.</note> that ſo it may gaine upon <hi>our owne things:</hi> which we will ſeeke through Chriſt in his Saints, and cauſe requires the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; Is this a time, ſaid the Prophet to <hi>Gehazi,</hi> to receive money and garments? So might <hi>Paul</hi> have ſaid to theſe tender <hi>delicate brethren,</hi> that were ſo <hi>unlike to Timothie;</hi> Is this a time to minde caſe, and reſt, and ſafety, and <hi>ſelfe?</hi> ſuch a kind of <hi>ſeeking our own things,</hi> muſt needs hinder the <hi>ſeeking the things of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> I have done with the firſt thing that I propounded to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pened, <hi>viz.</hi> what ſeeking it is that hinders us from ſeeking the <hi>things of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond followes,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Bran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of Expli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tion.</hi> Secondly, the point opened, by ſhe wing what things of Chriſt Self-ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king hinders us from ſeeking. 1. It hindred fró ſeeking and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding Chriſt a himſelf.</note> what things of Chriſt this ſelf-ſeeking hindereth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This cauſed a neglect of Chriſt himſelfe when he was here upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>th; even to an earneſt ſoliciting him ſometimes to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſts, Matth.</hi> 8.34. Sometimes it made people <hi>fearefull to acknowledge him, Iohn</hi> 9.22. At other time<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>openly to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him; Twas this that <hi>derided him in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Phariſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s, Luke</hi> 16.14. Twas this that <hi>perſecuted him in the Ruler<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Twas this that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 19.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Danyed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112931:10"/>him</hi> (ſo far as it prevailed) <hi>in Peter, Matth,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6.30. <hi>That bewayed him in Indas, Matth.</hi> 26.47. <hi>That conirived his death in the chief Prieſts,</hi> they were wholly bent upon preſetving their <hi>owne place</hi> and their nation, <hi>Iohn</hi> 11.48. Twas this that <hi>conde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ned him</hi> in <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, Luke</hi> 23.24. In a word, it made his whole life, <hi>a life of neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect,</hi> and 'twas the reaſon why <hi>Chriſt</hi> came to his owne, and his owne received him not. <hi>His owne ſought their owne things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Inordinate ſelf-regarding hath ever cauſed and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed a neglect of Chriſt and his things,<note place="margin">2 And from ſeeking the things of Chriſt in his ſervants.</note> in mens cariage toward his <hi>ſervants;</hi> What was it but this which made them accounted the burdens of the earth, the wondermen? of the world, the plagues of their ſeverall ages? they were againſt <hi>ſelfe,</hi> and <hi>ſelfe</hi> in every man was againſt them; Twas ſeeking their owne things that made <hi>Diana's worſhippers</hi> ſo loude in their out-cryes againſt Bleſſed <hi>Paul;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 19.28.</note> that made <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> threatned for that miracle of mercy; that impriſoned and abuſed the Apoſtles;<note place="margin">Acts 4.18.5.40<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that <hi>ſton<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ven</hi> for feacre of ſuffering a change in old and owne cuſtomes; that moved <hi>Herod</hi> to kill <hi>James,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 6.13.7.59<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Acts 12.3.</note> and endeavour the murder of <hi>Peter. Self-regarding</hi> was the winde that ever raiſed ſtormes againſt the <hi>ſervants of Chriſt;</hi> at the beſt it made them lookt upon with neglect and contempt, it made people fearfull to accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with them, <hi>or ioyne</hi> to their Societie;<note place="margin">Acts 5.19.</note> or if ſome did goe ſo fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as out ward Compliance with them, yet hath this <hi>ſelf-regarding</hi> cauſed ſquint-eyed aimes, and ſecret reſolutions upon occaſion of difficultie to forſake them. What but this hath neglected <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his diſtreſſed members, often denying reliefe to them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1 Sam. 25.11.</hi> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ties dixit me t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>; meum, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> tandem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit ſiant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rving <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his Saints? Was it not this that made <hi>Nabal</hi> branded with the name of a churle, and cauſed that unkinde deniall of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vias</hi> ſlender requeſt; Shall I give, ſaith he, <hi>my bread, my water, my fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, This immoderate regarding our own things,<note place="margin">From ſeeking the things of Chriſt in the cauſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</note> hath neglected the things of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the cauſe of Religi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n. What but this kept <hi>Meroz</hi> back from helping the <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd?</hi> What, if not this, detained <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nben</hi> among the <hi>ſheep-folds,</hi> to hear the <hi>bleating of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ocks,</hi> when the <hi>cauſe</hi> of God was in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>copa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dy?<note place="margin">Judg. 4. Chap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> This t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> to his <hi>ſhips;</hi> This ſhut up the hearts and hands of the men of <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccoth</hi> and <hi>Pennel</hi> againſt the Fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ting bodies of the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ers of Gods and his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hurches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. 'Twas the ſeeking
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112931:11"/>
               <hi>their own things</hi> that would have curſed the Church by <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>, Numb.</hi> 22. diſturbed it by <hi>Cora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 26.9. and 16.3. that aboliſhed the purity of worſhip out of the kingdom of <hi>Iſrael</hi> by <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12.26, 27. that hindered the full reformation of it in <hi>Jehu's</hi> time, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 10.19. that retarded the reformation after the <hi>Babyloniſh-captivity, Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch.</hi> 2.7.<note place="margin">Rom. 16.17.</note> In a word, all the home-bred <hi>diſtractions,</hi> and <hi>diviſions,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>unſound opinions, ſidings, half-reformations, ſinfull limitations,</hi> to go thus far, and no farther, ungodly bredths, which people have indulged to themſelves, <hi>wretched allowances</hi> of groſſe ſinnes, and errors in ſome, though perſecuting the appearances of them in others; all theſe, with infinite more, have ſelf-ſeeking in the Church for their ſource. This hath been ever the<note n="*" place="margin">Tine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> babet damnum, non ſonitum.</note> 
               <hi>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th</hi> of the Church,<note place="margin">Amariſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ma mea amaritudo in moribus domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum pax a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganis, ab haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cis, ſed non a filiis.</note> making up in hurt, what it wants in noiſe; <hi>Sions Still-Deſtroyer,</hi> to which the Church may ſay, as <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phtah</hi> to his dangli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I am, and ever was, brought low for thy ſake, O ſelf-ſeeking: and therefore holy <hi>Bernard</hi> makes it a greater enemy to the Church then the moſt raging perſecutions.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">4. And from ſeeking the things of Chriſt in his word, it hinders Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters by making them to be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſilent. Epheſ. 6.19. To adulterate it with humane wiſedom, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 2 Cor. 2.17. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſemper in fames habit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quod mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es adulterant.</hi> To wrack it for falſe opinions. Tit. 1.11. Phil. 3.19. 2 P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.1, 2, 3.</note> This ſeeking our own things, neglects the things of Chriſt in the <hi>preaching of the Word;</hi> Self-ſeeking hath made <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> and <hi>people</hi> neglect Chriſt in his Word: For <hi>Miniſters,</hi> it hath made them neglect the Word, ſometime by ſinfull ſilencing ſome truthes, and un worthy face-fearing; A ſinne, (ſo ready to creep into the Pulpit) that <hi>Paul</hi> deſires the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> Epheſ. 6.19. to pray it down, even in himſelf; At other times by corrupting and adulterating the truth with ſinner-ſoothing words (as wine with water) not <hi>the words of wiſdome, but the wiſdome of words,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, 1 <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rin.</hi> 1.17. all this while, they ſpeaking three words for themſelves, for one in the behalf of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time again <hi>Self-ſeeking</hi> hath corrupted the preaching of the Word, by putting Miniſters upon perverting it, for the upholding of impious opinions, <hi>gainfull to the purſe,</hi> and <hi>hurtfull to the heart;</hi> thus the Apoſtle ſpeaks of <hi>filthy lusre,</hi> that made ſome <hi>preach things</hi> which they <hi>ought not;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arthly mindedneſſe in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that cauſed enmity to the <hi>croſſe of Chriſt,</hi> (I conceive the Apoſtle means, their preaching the Law in a way of oppoſition to Chriſts ſatisfaction:) Covetouſneſſe and deſire to make mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndiſe of ſouls, puts others upon bringing in <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>able hereſies;</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:112931:11"/>At other times, ſelf-regarding hath put Miniſters upon preaching the Word, who are altogether uns<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>full, and unprepared,<note place="margin">To adventure upon preaching it unpreparedly.</note> work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that may well be aſhamed, never trained up to handle their ſpirituall atms, not like thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ilfull <hi>Beni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ites</hi> able to ſhoot at a <hi>hairs breadth,</hi> though too like them in being <hi>left handed;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 20.16.</note> atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to, and preaching of exhortation, but unable to meddle with doctrine, though God commands both; tormenting the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Texts, making them ſpeak what they never intended;<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.2. <hi>Vid. Cal. in loc.</hi>
               </note> dealing with the Scriptures as Chy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iſts with naturall bodies, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to extract that out of them,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.16.</note> which nature never put in them; wounding the Scriptures with their own weapons, and making them <hi>(Vriah-like)</hi> carry letters for their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            <p>Nor hath the Word fared better from <hi>ſelf-ſeeking hearers;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Self-ſeeking hinders people from ſeeking the things of Chriſt in the word; hereby they contemn the threatnings of it. Deut. 29.19. Hoſ. 12.7, 8. Luk. 16.12. <hi>Per hoc quod amant coguntur ad hoc quod vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant.</hi> Greg. 1 Tim. 6.9. 2. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of it. Ezek. 33.31.</note> For how have they diſregarded all the adminiſtrations of it? what have its <hi>threatnings</hi> been in allages to them but empty cracks? do they not <hi>bleſſe themſelves</hi> in the ſaddeſt denuntiations of it? placing their proſecutions of <hi>their own things</hi> as a skreen between themſelves and Gods wrath; Theſe they were that evermore <hi>deſpiſed</hi> and <hi>derided</hi> the ſharpeſt Sermons; <hi>inſtifying themſelves</hi> becauſe haply <hi>men</hi> had nothing to ſay againſt them, hardning their <hi>necks</hi> though oft reproved, if the threatnings be ſevere they care not, they will on in their purſuits, though the Word tell them, hell, and deſtruction, and perdition be in the way.</p>
            <p>For the commands of it, they will perhaps give them the hearing; but though the Miniſters be <hi>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vely ſong, and a pleaſant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ice, and one that can play well on an inſtrument, yet their words they will not do, for their hearts run after their covetous inquiries;</hi> and the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.2. gives the reaſon in that place, where he implies that the luſts of men are flatly oppoſite to the <hi>will</hi> of God: A heart ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t upon ſeeking the world, gives that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment to the Word, which <hi>Abraham</hi> gave to his ſervants who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id them ſtay behinde a while,<note place="margin">Gen. 22.5.</note> till he and his ſonne had gone <hi>to ſacr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> but then he comes again unto them: ſo theſe (if they can ſpare ſo much time) will for an hour in a week bid their <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arthly enquiries</hi> ſtay till they have heard what their <hi>preciſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructer</hi> will deliver, but then they'l after ward make up their <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>iſſion</hi> with a more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ager <hi>proſecution</hi> of all the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112931:12"/>and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>ſelf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> They who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nded in their affections, by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of health or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nength, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, or honour, ſhall we think that theſe will be reſtrained by <hi>precep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Gods own</hi> immediat <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Bal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 22.22.</note> how fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itleſſe was i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> up he gets him betim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he morning, as if his bed had been at full of thorns as his ſoul; add though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and again, theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruell thirſtings break through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iculti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>: What be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efit received <hi>Ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> from him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or his words, who was in his life a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sermon, as well as was his doctrine an audible Sermon againſt <hi>ſelf-ſeeking?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But perhaps the <hi>co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>promiſes</hi> in the word of <hi>Chriſt</hi> may finde better entertainment with <hi>ſelf-ſeeking</hi> hearers;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of it.</hi> Non invideram Deo coelum ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Luk. 14.</hi> Convivae invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantur ad coelum &amp; ſaturantur in terris. Conciſam &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forment creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nitatem quae divinae eſt veſtigium dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt &amp; ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rant; auguſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, original<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, ime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gram &amp; pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherrima<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unt. <hi>Nier.</hi> Litura placet, ſed vivum &amp; lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidum archety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum non delectat.</note> no, their carnall palats reliſh none of theſe delicacies; theſe things are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Aquavit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> offered to one in a ſwoon, who ſhuts his teeth the harder againſt it, by how much the more he wants it: what are the precious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ings of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity</hi> to him, but warm clothes to a dead c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>caſſe? Would God but grant him (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> read of one that pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt it in words) a thouſand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reſpit, to follow <hi>his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n things,</hi> and to find a certain proportion of honour, wealth, and pleaſure, he would not envie God his heaven: D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th not <hi>Chriſt</hi> tell us, that they ſet light <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, and deſire to be excuſed from the troubleſome participation of the <hi>Evangelicall Supper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> their ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks are ſo clog'd with theſe <hi>own things,</hi> that the things of <hi>Chriſt</hi> have no room left for them; any thing from God pleaſeth them more then himſelf; If at any time they commend the good things of the Goſpel, it is not from any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt of ſwee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſſe in them, but it is meer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly a commendation upon hearſay, and to comply with the really taken with <hi>Chriſt.</hi> There are ſome hounds wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in hunting make a very loud noiſe, but it is not from anyſent they have of the Hare, but onely in imitation of the reſt: A heart eagerly ſet upon any luſting for <hi>ſelf,</hi> in all its ſeeming deligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> or <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>eter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity,</hi> findes no true ſweetheſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>in them, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> rather in his eſtimate lock upon them as very poor things: It thinks the <hi>life of faith, dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> upon a ſword<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to bee <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ich in reverſion,</hi> &amp;c. meer <hi>empty ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tions and notions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third branch of e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>phcation.</p>
            <p>The inordinate ſeeking our own things doth<note n="*" place="margin">Poſſunt manere in e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem animarum curare, &amp;c. ſed ita ut m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rera babeant rationem ſui commodi, &amp;c. <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nch.</hi> in loc.</note> not hinde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all manor of ſeeking the things of Ieſus Chriſt; for <hi>ſelf-ſeekers,</hi> may be employed in governing, preaching, &amp;c. in the Church.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:112931:12"/>
            <p>But it hinders from ſeeking them,<note place="margin">3. Branch of explication. What hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the things of Chriſt the ſeeking of our own things cauſeth. 1. Self-ſeeking hinders from ſeeking the things of Chriſt Inwardly. Exod. 3.2. Ezek. 33.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Heartily; inwardly. A ſelf-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ker ſeekes the things of Ieſus Chriſt ſeemingly, superficially onely;</hi> like ſome men who lifting with others at a burden, it may be make as great a noiſe, and as l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d a cry as the reſt, but yet they put to it no ſtrength at all; A ſelf-ſeeker commonly makes the greateſt noiſe, and doth the leaſt work; his fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is like that in the buſh, which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaw, making a great flame but not burning at all. <hi>Iehu</hi> was in appearance a great <hi>ſeeker</hi> of God, and reformation, he made a great noiſe; but his heart was never further from ſeeking the things of God, then when he was ſeeking them. He did but act a reformer. The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that heard <hi>Ezekiels</hi> Sermons made much out ward appearance of delight in them, but their hearts went after ſelf-proſecutions; A <hi>Chriſt-ſeeker</hi> contrarily is more then he can expreſſe <hi>for Chriſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Non magna lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quimur, ſed vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vimus. <hi>Cypr.</hi> de pat.</note> hath a heart within whereof all he doth for Chriſt out watdly, like an Interpreter that reacheth not the emphaſis of the originall, cannot fully expreſſe the love it be a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th to <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Lord take it, ſaith hee, bee it life, limb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, wealth, &amp;c. and oh that they were better for thy ſake!</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. From ſeeking them ſolely.</note> Self-ſeeking hindereth from ſeeking the <hi>things of Ieſus Chriſt ſolely, and by themſelves alone.</hi> A ſelf-ſeeker regards not Chriſt unleſſe his work hath ſome attendances of honour, wealth,<note place="margin">Chriſtus non dulce, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t propter ſeipſum. <hi>Bern. See Hoſ. 10.11. 2 King. 3.14.</hi> Coelum apertum ſt, &amp; Deum non quaerit, aurum abſcouſion eſt &amp; terrae viſcera recludit. <hi>1 Cor. 10.30. Phil. 1.18.</hi> Valde perſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſt ſic often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo opere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> glori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rere ut de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de priv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciant g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re. <hi>Greg.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> pleaſure; like little children that love not a leſſon wherein there is not a <hi>gay;</hi> Plaine work and ſervice which is not fring'd with honour, wealth, <hi>obſervation of the people, &amp;c.</hi> hee goeth about very liſtleſly: As <hi>Eliah</hi> ſaid to <hi>Aha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> that if it were not <hi>for Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſhaphats preſence</hi> he would not ſo much as beſtow a look upon him; ſo thinks the <hi>ſelf-ſeeker,</hi> were not rewards preſent, renown preſent, applauſe preſent <hi>with Chriſts ſervice,</hi> he would not regard it; ſee how different this temper is from that of a <hi>Chriſt. ſeeker:</hi> Could <hi>Paul</hi> but ſave ſouls, he regarded not his own profit or name, bee cared not whether that were preſent or no. A Saint ſaith as that noble Commander, who being to undertake an expedition of danger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and thereupon diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aded, reſolvedly anſwered, 'Tis not neceſſary I ſhould live, but that the work ſhould be done; and is the work brought about, he cares nor though his induſtry, fidelity, parts, prudence, all lie hid; nay hee fear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to diſcover them for gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying of ſelf, as <hi>Moſes parents</hi> were afraid hee ſhould be ſeen,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112931:13"/>becauſe he was fair, and therefore hid him in the ark.</p>
            <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">3. From ſeeking them comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably.</note> 
               <hi>It hinders from ſeeking Chriſts things comfortably and with reioycing;</hi> The building of comfort is onely ſet upon the foundation of integrity: A <hi>ſelf-ſeeker</hi> is left of God to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, after employment, by him that ſet him on work; hee hath an unpacified ſpirit, in all the applauſes, and admirations that he meets with from men; hee can never be quieted from God, that is not employed by God; God hath reſerved this reward of joy, onely for his owne ſervice; an unſound crazy heart can never hold that precious liquor.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See 2 Cor. 1.12.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum cordis quo dolor omnís a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ceptae levatur iniuriae. <hi>Ambr.</hi> in Pſal. <hi>36.</hi> praef. <hi>1 Chron. 29.14.</hi>
               </note> If the ſervice go croſſe, the <hi>Chriſt-ſeeker</hi> is comforted by the integrity of his aimes. <hi>David</hi> was not permitted to build the Temple, yet hee rejoyced at his own, and <hi>his people willingneſſes,</hi> 1 Chron. 29. A <hi>ſelf-ſeeker</hi> when he doth effect any thing advantagious to the cauſe of Chriſt, leaves all the joy of that ſervice to him that <hi>loves Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> the one laboureth, and the other enters into his labours.</p>
            <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">4. Self-ſeeking hinders from ſeeking the things of Chriſt throughly.</note> 
               <hi>It hinders from ſeeking Chriſts things throughly.</hi> A <hi>ſelf-ſeeker</hi> ever ſets him ſelf bounds, thus far he will go, and no further, this abuſe (is hee a Magiſtrate) hee will reform, not the other; this man ſhall bee puniſht when hee refuſeth the Covenant, not another; He aimes not at the doing the work of Chriſt to beauty, perfection, and exactneſſe; put caſe, at the firſt hee endeavours the reíormation of idolatry, prophaneneſſe, hereſies, &amp;c. nay cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants too that he will do ſo, yet if his own end bee ſerved once, and his own way permitted, let Popery, or the worſt of abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations go untoucht afterward he cares not; ſo that his ſtudying for a reformation, is like ſome Gentlemens ſtudy of the Law, into which they deſire to get no further inſight, then only for the ſaving their own eſtates; the employment that is eaſie and ſafe he undertakes,<note place="margin">Propter Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam nolunt magna ſubire pericula, ſed cum Chriſto volunt eſſe, coniunctas ſuas delicias. <hi>Zanc. in loc. Act. 20.24. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Cor. 10.33.</hi>
               </note> withdraws from another more difficult, like to one that hath an unſound foot, who picks out the ſofteſt way to travell in, and if hee muſt goe in a hard way, there hee hal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s; Many acts of <hi>Chriſts ſervice</hi> are too high for <hi>ſelfe</hi> to carry us upon, too irrationall for ſelf apprehenſion to ſubmit unto, too dangerous <hi>for ſelfs</hi> tenderneſſe to adventure in; <hi>A ſelf-ſeeker</hi> loves not to ingage too deeply, leſt he ſhould never come off ſafe; a heart truely above <hi>ſelf</hi> is onely above <hi>fears,</hi> ſee it in the Apoſtle <hi>Paul;</hi> nothing moved him, neither did he account his <hi>life deare ſo as he might finiſh his Miniſterie with ioy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:112931:13"/>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Self-ſeeking hinders from ſeeking the things of Chriſt fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vently, zealouſly,</hi> with our might: the cream, and floure of our abilities are taken off for <hi>ſelf;</hi> performances that come not from the heart, are done ſlightly, and coldly;<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.1.</note> 
               <hi>the tongue will be no ready writer,</hi> unleſſe the heart be boyling with a good matter; our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices will never be coſtly, unleſſe the heart be full of affection; that's the reaſon that a ſelf-ſocker whoſe ſouls bent is ſet for his own things, is ſo dead, ſo faint, ſo liſtleſſe for God. When the ſpleen ſwels, all the other parts decay, and when we are much in ſatisfying <hi>ſelf,</hi> out ſervices for God are but lean, and thin, and ſlight: a divided heart betwixt Chriſt and ſelf, will bee a lazy heart. The eye that ſhould look <hi>toward Chriſt,</hi> will never bee ſharp-ſighted, unleſſe that which looks <hi>toward ſelf</hi> be ſhut, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther put out.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It hinders from <hi>ſeeking Chriſts things conſtantly.</hi> A ſelf-ſeeker wants a principle, a fountain, from whence to iſſue his ſervices. A ſtanding pool, or a ſhallow plaſh of water will ſoon dry up, ſo will his goodneſſe that wants the heart to feed it.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 6.4.</note> 
               <hi>'Tis onely a friend that loves at all times;</hi> hee that ſeeks the things of Chriſt for fear of authority, for love of credit, gain, &amp;c. when theſe ceaſe, his ſearch will ceaſe alſo. The redneſſe of bluſhing in the face, is ſoon down again;<note place="margin">Prov. 17.17.</note> 'tis that of the naturall complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that onely continues; A man that is high and hot in his ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, will ſoon bee low, and cold again, if there bee not a holy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalneſſe, an inward integrity in the ſoul, for the things of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I have done with the third and laſt branch of explication, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the hinderances ſtand, that the ſeeking of our own things cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth: I come to the ſecond thing I intend in the proſecution of this point, <hi>viz.</hi> the confirmation.</p>
            <p>Every in ordinate luſting after any thing that concerns <hi>our ſelves, takes up, ingroſſeth,</hi> and <hi>menopelizeth,</hi> as it were,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Inordinate luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for ſelf takes up the whole man, in what he is, and doth.</note> 
               <hi>the whole man,</hi> and gives way to it to attend upon nothing but its own ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, unleſſe by the way, and ſo farre forth as its maine drift may not bee hindered: As in the regular and due beſtowing our hearts and ſearches upon God and his wayes,<note n="*" place="margin">Qui tua ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi cententione in unum Deum defertur, in plura ſtudia animum non pert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tur. <hi>Cal. in Matt. 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4.</hi>
               </note> there's an affording
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:112931:14"/>the whole man to them, and it there be any other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eject comes in the way,<note place="margin">Non exhibitione ceremoniarum, ſed ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ione con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>upiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. <hi>Gregor.</hi>
               </note> a Saint that makes God his chiefe end gives it but a ſlight ſalute, and ſo <hi>uſeth it, as if be uſed it not:</hi> Thus it is with thoſe that reſign and deliver their affection to the power of any enquiry, or employment whatſoever: of there be any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> luſting in a way of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> allow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a gh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ployes the whole man;<note place="margin">Am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſt qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſui e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itus, quaedam a ſe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regrinati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntaria m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. Ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. de arte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as all our endeavors were made for a god, ſo they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> make a god, or finde a god; and if ſo, what can be expected for the <hi>things of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> but that they ſhould bee lookt after in the ſecond place, very poorly, if at all, in a way of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſerviencie to ſelf, and at the allowance of luſt? If honours for our ſelv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, wealth, pleaſures, revenge, be the end we propound, the whole man will be employed for the accompliſhment.</p>
            <p>The <hi>underſtanding</hi> will undervalue any thing elſe in compar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on,<note place="margin">1. The under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</note> it admire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>that highly which the heart is ſet upon, ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſesſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime eſtimates upon it.<note place="margin">Quiſquis amat ranam, ranam putas eſſe Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am.</note> O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hinksit, had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> this, or that, I were made for over; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thinks there's no other <hi>heaven</hi> but <hi>wealth,</hi> and <hi>honour,</hi> things ſutable to the corrupted faculty.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>will and affections,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. The will and affections.</note> they will bee employed about the proſecution of the thing principally ſought after, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ither wealth, or honour, or the like; that thing will he <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſous ſpirit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> the wings of the af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ctions will bee ſo beſmeared with it,<note place="margin">Quando dulceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it mundus, ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it Deus.</note> there will be no ſoaring God-ward. Hee'l grow bitter when the world is ſweet; and there is ſuch a <hi>twiſting, and<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt wining</hi> of the affections within one another, that all will be entangled about that object which is principally purſued; the <hi>ioy</hi> in pleaſing it ſelf with it if o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ained,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the <hi>deſire</hi> in craving it if wanted, the <hi>hope</hi> in expecting it if probable, the <hi>anger</hi> in overcomming if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, the <hi>grief</hi> in lamenting if removed; And what's now left for the things of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>thoughts</hi> they will bee buſied with,<note place="margin">3. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oughts.</note> and buried in <hi>ſelfe-employments;</hi> God <hi>being not ſought,</hi> hee will not <hi>bee in all the thoughts;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 10.4.</note> the thoughts of <hi>remembrance,</hi> of <hi>contrivance, enquiry,</hi> will all bee ſet upon theſe <hi>own things;</hi> theſe will onely buſie the brain. The <hi>thought<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> are like a mill, alway turning, and the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>love</hi> throws in the grain and ſeed which they grind; if it therefore bee ſet upon <hi>ſelf,</hi> what but <hi>ſelf and own things</hi> can bee
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:112931:14"/>put into the thoughts; the afflictions of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> will be forgotten, the welfare of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the ſafety of <hi>Sion</hi> will bee uninquired into, theſe <hi>own things</hi> will take up all the <hi>thoughts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>tongue which speaks out of the abundance of the heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. The to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note> will altogether talk of earthly proſecutions; as what kinde of goods fill the ſhop within, will hang upon the ſtall without; ſo if the hearts ſearches be for <hi>ſelf,</hi> the tongues enquiries will be ſo too; <hi>Earthy and ſpeaking of the earth</hi> are put together;<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.31.</note> ſo if there bee ſelf-ſeeking, ſpeaking for ſelf will follow. The hand of the Clock doth but ſhew how the wheels go within. An unſavory ſtomack will not ſend forth a ſweet breath; earthy hearts will ſend forth a breath in common talking, like to the breath of dying man, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring onely of the earth: Where then will bee the tongue for the <hi>things of Chriſt, the directing tongue, the encouraging tongue, the commanding tongue?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>actions</hi> will bee employed,<note place="margin">5. The actions.</note> and ſteerd according to the motions of <hi>love.</hi> A <hi>ſelf-minding-man</hi> will do nothing for <hi>Chriſt;</hi> If <hi>ſelf</hi> have withdrawn the <hi>heart,</hi> 'twill <hi>wither the hand toe.</hi> There will be no contributing <hi>hand</hi> for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or his <hi>truth,</hi> or his <hi>members,</hi> commonly 'tis employed in receiving onely; If it parts with ought, commonly it comes by conſtraint; it gives as a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row mouth'd bottle ſends forth water, with a muttering; If the Law will enforce nothing, truly conſcience will beſtow nothing; If any thing prevaile with it, 'twill be death, then perhaps like a poor mans box, when broken, a <hi>ſelf-ſeeker</hi> may afford ſomewhat; when the cauſe of God craves his aſſiſtance, where's his <hi>helping hand?</hi> he had rather the <hi>Church</hi> ſhould for ever ſtick in the mire of miſerie then lend her it; never will he ſtretch it forth, though to the raiſing up the poor fainting Spouſe of Chriſt; He is ſo worn out, and wearied in <hi>ſelf-employments,</hi> that <hi>Chriſts things</hi> muſt be neglected; hee burns out the taper of his ſtrength, wealth, parts, in doing his own works, when Chriſts things are to be done, the candle's out.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee this inordinate ſeeking our own things, takes up the whole man, in what hee is and does. That's the firſt Reaſon. But,</p>
            <p>Secondly, It takes not onely in him and of him up all;<note place="margin">2. <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </note> but all
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112931:15"/>this <hi>unweariedly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of luſting for ſelf, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſant.</note> unceſſantly where 'tis allowed, there is an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging without meaſure, therefore called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an effuſion, a ruſhing out of luſtings, an <hi>aeſtus</hi> like the foaming or boyling of the ſea.<note place="margin">Quitquid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tur tanquam finis quaeritur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulla adhibita m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſura. <hi>1. Pet. 4.4. Eſ. 55.2.</hi> Oblitus Dei vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatem occupas, non imples; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reaturae non ſunt ad occupandum volumatem, ſed ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uvandum memoriam. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mentem, non ſatisfaciunt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mori.</note> Theſe ſinfull ſearchings can never be caried to any thing in w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they may reſt, therefore they will be alway in motion; for though there be not enough in the things they follow to ſatisfie them, yet there is enough perpetually to entice them. Deſires and ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are like <hi>numbers,</hi> one can never goe ſo farre in numbring, but there may be a number named beyond it, and above it; ſo there are ever more remaining deſires, <hi>a reſerve of deſires</hi> (as I may ſay) in the heart, <hi>freſh ſupplies new raiſed,</hi> whenſoever any old ones are cloyd or clogd; (for ſo they are rather then ſatisfied) It may be ſaid of theſe luſtings, when wee endeavour to fill them, as 'twas of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> when the <hi>Egyptians</hi> endeavoured to ſuppreſſe and deſtroy them, they grew the more in numbers and ſtrength, the more they were oppreſſed. God whoſe commands t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd not to the impoveriſhing of the body (as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith) hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd time and employment, and wealth ſufficient for needfull proviſions, nay ſometime for delight, and as <hi>God</hi> ſaith to <hi>David,</hi> If this <hi>had not beenenough, thus and thus could I have done for thee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> but a man that alloweth himſelfe in his luſts and proſecutions for ſelf, breaks over the hedge of ſufficiency into the wide Common of exceſs, and there loſeth himſelfe. <hi>Oh the prodigious unwearyed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of a man ſet upon any ſearching <hi>for ſelf!</hi> the carkaſs, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument may be worne and wearied out, but the luſting is never tired, ther's a wearineſs perhaps of <hi>ſervice</hi> in the <hi>members,</hi> but none of <hi>command</hi> in the <hi>Law;</hi> ſo the Prophet, <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u art wearied in thy way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſ. 57.10.</note> yet ſaidſt thou not there <hi>is no hope;</hi> though thou art out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly tired in the proſecutions <hi>of luſts,</hi> yet thou ſayeſt not, Iſe give over, my <hi>hopes</hi> are not yet at an end; thou ſtill dreameſt of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, and therefore wilt go on with wonted madnes;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>upiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>entia non ſeneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it.</note> 
               <hi>A luſt out-lives its facultie;</hi> concupiſcence never groweth crazie in the weakeſt body, if the facultie could, luſt would ſtill riſe up early, lie downe late,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ab. 2.6.</note> lade it ſelfe with <hi>thicke clay,</hi> how ever 'tis ſtill wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, woulding, <hi>ſeeking theſe owne things;</hi> what time is now left for the things of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> viati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um.</note> not ſo much as the dregs of ſicknes or old age, for the luſt is ſtill ſtrong and young, and craving, when life is ending.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:112931:15"/>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>The inordinate allowance of our induſtries in ſelf-ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reaſon</hi> 3. Luſting for ſelf, is directly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the things of Chriſt. Mat. 6.24.</note> muſt needs hinder us from ſeeking the things of Ieſus Chriſt, in regard of the oppoſitnes and repugnancie betweene our cravings and ſearchings, and the Worke and will of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> the one with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands the purſuit of the other. There can be no ſerving theſe two <hi>oppoſite maſters;</hi> if one be <hi>loved ſought,</hi> the other will be loathed; inordinate affection drawes one way, the will <hi>of Chriſt</hi> another; like the two women that were pleading for the living childe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Solomon,</hi> but with this difference, <hi>the things of Chriſt,</hi> and ſelf, both plead, but neither will admit of a diviſion, a parting of the height of our enquiries;<note place="margin">Phil. 3.19.</note> there can be no accommodation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene inordinate inquiries, and Chriſtian. <hi>Enmity to Chriſt is in ſeeking theſe earthly things;</hi> they are like two balances, if the one goe up, the other goeth downe, the ſerving of Chriſt and of our owne bellies cannot ſtand together.<note place="margin">Rom. 16.17<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> It's impoſſible to looke heaven-ward and earth-ward at the ſame time in this ſpirituall ſenſe. Self-enquiries like the womans diſeaſe in the Goſpel, bowes us downe to the earth, the <hi>ſeekings of Chriſt</hi> require eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. When the Moone is at full its directly oppoſite to the Sun, when our hearts and enquiries are fully ſet upon ſelfe, they will then oppoſe <hi>Chriſt;</hi> Indeed tis not impoſſible to doe our <hi>owne things,</hi> or to delight in the bleſſings God beſtowes upon us,<note place="margin">Nem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> poteſt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiri affect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſquis ſe in ſervitut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m divitiis tradit, Deo ſe emancipe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> neceſſe eſt. <hi>Calv. in 6. Mat.</hi>
               </note> and at the ſame to <hi>ſeek Chriſts things too,</hi> but then the maine aime and ſcope of the heart will be for God, and our other deſires, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights will be onely in a way of ſubordination and reference; as put caſe, <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſteward when he was in the journey had faire weather and uninterrupted paſſage, and pleaſant rode, theſe might have delighted him, and theſe he might before have deſired, but yet not ſo as to take off his minde from the maine end, for which <hi>Abraham</hi> ſent him forth, but ſo as hereby he might be the more enabl'd to do his Maſters buſines; God ownes not ſervices which have not him for the maine ſcope, at leaſt which endeavour it not; the inordinate ſeekings of ſelfe are oppoſite to thoſe of Chriſt; Chriſt may have many ſeekers, but theſe ſeekers cannot have many Chriſts.<note place="margin">3. <hi>Application.</hi> 1. Inference fró the premiſes.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The ſinne and miſery of a man enthralled to any one luſting for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:112931:16"/>ſelfe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Vſe.</hi> He is 1. unſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to Chriſt. <hi>In mundo ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> qui hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem Dei non quaerit.</hi> Lzek. 15.3.</note> he is detained from doing any thing for Ieſus Chriſt; he is a meer uſeleſs Drone, a Cipher, a Mute, a Nullitie; Certainely, a <hi>Superſedeas from ſerving Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> would bee to a gracious heart the greateſt burden in the world; This is his condition that is a ſlave to himſelfe, he's like the branches of a Vine fit for nouſe in building a houſe, meet for doing no work, good for nothing but the fire; he is a meer <hi>broken Idoll,</hi> a <hi>veſſell of no pleaſure,</hi> no wayes <hi>fitted for the Maſters uſe;</hi> hee is one that diverteth himſelfe from the ſcope to which God directs him, one that is drawne from the uſe agreed upon in heaven; (nothing in the creature being or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd for it ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, as light in the ſunne, water in the well, both are for man, and man for God.) When he is about theſe owne things, he is in Gods account as if he were doing <hi>nothing,</hi> as <hi>Chriſt</hi> tells <hi>his Diſciples, they</hi> had hitherto <hi>asked nothing,</hi> becauſe they had onely deſired worldly greatneſſe,<note place="margin">Iohn 16.24.</note> honour, promotions, &amp;c. So they that give over themſelves to theſe <hi>ſelfe employments worke nothing, ſeeke nothing;</hi> This would be a hell to a Saint, though it deſerved not another to follow it. But then to leave all the <hi>things of Chriſt</hi> even for <hi>luſts ſake,</hi> this greatens the miſerie; if it were for ſomthing els, neare as good that a man neglected <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> If for another Chriſt, another Maſter that could <hi>love him as dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, uſe him as kindly, provide for him as plentifully, reward him as liberally, employ him as nobly;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. A ſlave to his luſtings which are 1. Very many. Multitude of Perſecutions. <hi>Quam multos babet Dominos qui unum non babet!</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3.33. 2. Very vile. Hab. 2.6. <hi>Home ad m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>talla damnatus.</hi>
               </note> the wonder of wretchednes were not ſo great: But in not <hi>ſeeking Chriſt,</hi> know O man (if thou do'ſt not rather unman thy ſelfe by leaving thy God) that thou ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicteſt thy ſelfe to thoſe ſearchings and ſervings that thy owne luſts impoſe upon thee, thy luſts which are in number many, thou muſt be peſter'd with many ſatanicall ſwarmes of them, when thou forſakeſt one Lord, all haling and tugging thy ſoule to diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and (in a ſort) oft times oppoſite employments; among which thou art but <hi>Pila diaboli,</hi> the devils Ball, which he by thine owne luſtings toſſeth hither and thither.</p>
            <p>Thy proſecutions are vile and low, and unworthy they are the ladings of thy ſelfe with thick clay, wallowings of a ſwine, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they might have been the workings a Saint, nay an Angel. Thon art one that invites luſt to enter upon the goods of God himſelf,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:112931:16"/>one that appropriates to that abomination what is dedicated to a holy uſe, worſe then <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> carouſing in the golden veſſells of the Temple, or one who digs in a dunghill with a golden ſpade. God hath beſtowed a veſſell, a ſpirit of gold, admirable abilities and endowments, and theſe are at the devotion of luſt, upon which are beſtowed Wells that they never digged, vineyards that they never planted, a ſoule, and endowments that they never cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>1. Sam. 5.5.</hi> Aguoſce digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem tuam Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiane, &amp; factus conſors divina naturae noli te in tantam vilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem deijcere. Vbiar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> antiq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mo co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>taneus homini cum voluit eſſe ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut Deus? Cohaeres Chriſti, collega Angelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, congaudet ſocictatipecorum, Dei gremio &amp; dulci amplexu ſe abjungit. Nier. Praepoſtera pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia. Mend. Privilegio quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam patientiae honoramus dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na noſtra ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus nos. Nunqua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> liber a compodibus que ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mper in crime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus. <hi>Greg.</hi>
               </note>The <hi>Philiſtines</hi> would not ſuffer the feet of men to tread upon that threſhold, upon which their but fictitious and ſuppoſed <hi>Deitie</hi> had fallen, but thou admitteſt that which is baſer then a toad, nay a devill (Satans excrement, as <hi>Bernard</hi> calls it) to trample upon that excellent nature which God aſſumed, which is capable of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine nature here, and of participation of the preſence of the great God to eternitie; thou goeſt as farre beneath thy ſelfe, as a King doth in ſtopping an Oven with his Robes, or in ſhaking hay with his Scepter. When a Saint is taking a turne in the <hi>Ivorie Palaces,</hi> hath his heart and head buſied in and for heaven, and walks even hand in hand with Angels, and is buſied in the employments <hi>of Chriſt,</hi> then is a ſinner toiling in the vile drudgerie of luſt, he is by a <hi>prepoſterous patience</hi> a true ſlaviſh <hi>Cham,</hi> a ſervant of ſervants, an embracer of a dunghill, nay, a ſlave to that which God did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver make, that is now invited to deſtroy his creature.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>3. Very tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall.</hi> Deus eſt centrum quietati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um animae. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>git amor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra alveare ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. <hi>Iſaiah 50.11.</hi>
               </note>And theſe proſecutions are as <hi>cruell and tyrannicall,</hi> as they are vile and abominable, ther's never any peace in them. The Bee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſtings but when out of the hive; nor the affections but when out of the embracements of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> this is <hi>thy portion to lie downe in ſorrow;</hi> every employment for luſt is an affrightment; no peace from God but in the ſervice of the God of peace. All ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings for ſelf are<note n="c" place="margin">Both in their employments which are bitter. And inceſſant.</note> ſoul-ſcratchings, they are <hi>thornes</hi> to rend the ſpirit, which God hath interwoven in every ſervice of luſt; the uncertaine profits and pleaſures which thou aimeſt at, are but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing huskie goods, but the evils which neceſſarily attend, are true and reall evills and troubles.</p>
            <p>What ſhall I ſay of that inceſſancy of toile which thou under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goeſt in theſe workes of crueltie? It's a true ſpeech, <hi>Peccator nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam feriatur,</hi> this cager purſuer of any inordinate luſting keepes
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112931:17"/>no holy-dayes; when he is upon his bed of Downe, then hee is pierced with theſe thornes of diſtraction and care,<note place="margin">An tu hunc ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m ſeli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m vocas, qui in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tem fort is eſt? cui pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum fallax um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra prae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>entiam aeternas congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat cauſas malo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram? quis bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xerit va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidam in ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m ingulum dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram? <hi>Nier.</hi> Ultrix miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia. <hi>Bern.</hi> Vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Domine iraſcaris ira qua corrigis devium, non qua extrudis de via. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </note> he caries a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of tortures in his breaſt: 'tis true, ſometimes Satan gives (and God in juſtice permits) a dream of joy, a little of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like contentment, in the hope or acquiring of ſome vaine gaine, or pleaſure: but theſe are but ſick ſlumbers; how cruell muſt thoſe ſleeps bee, which are upon the knees of a <hi>Delilah?</hi> and poured upon thee by an enemy? What-ever ſeeming good thou at tameſt in this way, 'tis but an <hi>angry mercy,</hi> thou uſeſt it as a meer bribe to the areſts of conſcience, which one day never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe will do his office: The raw-fleſh that is laid to the Wolf in the breaſt, will not alway laſt, and when 'tis devoured, then that living diſeaſe gnawes upon the tortured patient; All thy profits, pleaſures, honours, do but while-away, and neither truly intermit, nor to be ſure, aboliſh thy ſorrows; there's the root of all vexation in thee, departure from God <hi>in Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though thy very work bee a diſmall puniſhment, and a ſufficient torture in the apprehenſion of a Saint, yet the wages of all theſe out-goings of ſoul from thy God, ſhall be puniſhment even to the height: All thoſe honours,<note place="margin">And after their employments, in reſpect of their wages.</note> gaines, or pleaſures, for the ſake whereof thou haſt toyl'd and drudg'd ſo much in this world, even to a <hi>neglect of Chriſt,</hi> will all leave thee, (had there been as much pains taken for <hi>Chriſts things,</hi> they would have followed thee) as <hi>Abſaloms Mule</hi> did him,<note place="margin">Vitam noſtram centies potius op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponere debemus, quam brevem neſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>io quot dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum uſuram timi do filentio redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere. <hi>Calv ep.</hi> Quiſque ſeipſion prae Deo amat, nec ſeipſum, nec Deum amat. <hi>Aug.</hi> Per hoc quod aman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> coguntur ad hoc quod vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Greg.</hi>
               </note> when hee was hang'd in the tree: How much better will it then appeare to thee, if thou hadſt neglected a hundred gains, and undergone as many deaths for the <hi>things of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> then by reaſon of a ſhort and troubleſome proſecution of thine own things, to loſe thy God and ſelf too? how true then will that ſpeach bee found; <hi>Hee that loves himſelf above Chriſt, loves neither himſelf nor Chriſt?</hi> How gladly would'ſt thou then throw back with <hi>Iudas thy thirty peeces of ſilver,</hi> all thoſe gains, which thou perhaps didſt get in betraying the cauſe of <hi>Chriſt?</hi> then how wilt thou ſecond Gods condemning thee with <hi>ſelf-condemnation</hi> for thy folly, in preferring a childiſh <hi>gay</hi> before an advantagious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance; In being ſo deluded by Satan, who though heretofore he (like <hi>Solomons</hi> buyer) ſaid, 'Tis naught, 'tis naught, <hi>Chriſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:112931:17"/>and Religion,</hi> &amp;c. are nothing worth, yet now he hath guld thy ſoule of them, goeth away and laugheth at thee. Oh that (belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) you would thinke what dammage it is to lay out your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries altogether for receivings, while you never thinke of being received; none buyeth ſo deare and ſelleth ſo cheap,<note place="margin">Sic recipe ut re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piaris.</note> as he that by ſeeking his owne things, will <hi>part with Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> my laſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference will more fully cleare this, I ſhall not here therefore pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>I have done with the firſt. A ſecond and a more cloſe one fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes. 2. Inference.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Inference.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The ſeeking our owne things hath been the cauſe why the things of Chriſt have beene neglected in England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The things of Ieſus Chriſt as they</hi> reſpect his ſervants,<note place="margin">1. In his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</note> 
               <hi>his Miniſters eſpecially,</hi> how have they beene neglected? and oh that I could ſay but neglected and no more! Hath not <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his ſervants and <hi>Miniſters</hi> beene <hi>ſummus Martyr,</hi> the greateſt Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr? As <hi>Luther</hi> once ſaid in reſpect of the imputation of their ſins, Chriſt was <hi>Summus peccator</hi> the greateſt ſinner; may not we as <hi>confidently affirme</hi> that he hath ever been the <hi>ſoreſt ſufferer</hi> in his ſaints? Hath not our Engliſh ſoile been dyed with the blood of the Saints of Chriſt? hath it not bin the ſhambles of his innocent lambes in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, who was the rod upon the back of this poore Kingdom in the hand of God, for his Churches wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe under his indulgencies, in godly King <hi>Edwards</hi> Reigne? ſince, though the quiet aſhes of thoſe bleſſed Martyrs could not be diſturbed, yet hath not Martyrdome riſen againe? 'Tis plaine it hath, I, &amp; that ſometime even to reſiſtance <hi>unto blood;</hi> not to doubt but <hi>that it was</hi> even in the calmer reigne of that cruell Queenes two next Succeſſors, (though it durſt not appeare ſo publiquely, as in Smithfield) hath it not of late ſhew'd it ſelfe with an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldned brow; ſhould I either doubt of, or deny it, you might aske me whether I am the onely <hi>ſtranger in Ieruſalem?</hi> nay theſe <hi>things</hi> have not <hi>beene done or ſuffered in a corner,</hi> not our ſelves at home, but even all the Proteſtants in <hi>Europe,</hi> (and oh that wee had never ſent the tidings hereof to <hi>America)</hi> have with aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment beheld them; who hath not heard of the whippings,<note place="margin">In time of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laticall tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie.</note> the brandings, the baniſhments, and impriſonments of many precious Saints? how frequent was it for <hi>a Ceremonie</hi> which never ſearc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:112931:18"/>could get beyond the commendation of a <hi>tolerable triſte,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive the moſt learned and godly Miniſters of not living only, but all livelyhood, health and habitation, (the beggering their wives and children, and the ſtarving of their flockes being counted but a trifle) and what might be the cauſe why theſe <hi>things of Ieſus Chriſt</hi> went ſo to the wrack? did <hi>Prelats</hi> thinke we offer theſe ſacrifices to a dull drie Ceremonie a poſture of the bodie, or the table? no there was the <hi>ſeeking of theſe owne things;</hi> higher pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions for ſelfe, more gratious lookes from Superiours, a more glittering attendance <hi>forſelfe,</hi> theſe things put them upon theſe furious courſes; now Ceremonies and preferments are ſevered, there are not more forward men in the world (I ſpeake upon knowledge) then many late admirers of Prelacie, to cry downe what heretofore they ſo eagerly voyced up; But have the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſters of <hi>Chriſt</hi> beene better uſed by <hi>ſelfe ſeeking</hi> of late? ſurely no.<note place="margin">Diabolus mutat ingenium, non depouit od<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um.</note> Satan changeth his colours, never his conditions; now the moſt ſtrictly pious and couragious of them in times of Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, who did not (durſt not) leave their flockes to flie for more ſafetie and plentie elſewhere; but ſtood it out like <hi>Davids Worthy againſt</hi> hundreds of oppoſitions; theſe (I ſay) who thorowout the whole Kingdome have been the greateſt inſtruments of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, weeping,<note place="margin">And of ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall fury.</note> preaching, living downe <hi>Anti-chriſt,</hi> muſt now be counted and called the limbes of <hi>Anti-chriſt;</hi> no diſgraces thought enough to aſperſe them and their doctrine; But what's the cauſe of this neglect of the <hi>ſervants of Chriſt?</hi> ſurely this <hi>ſelf-ſeeking lies</hi> at the bottome;<note place="margin">Self things.</note> either <hi>ſelfe thinks</hi> their doctrine too ſharp, their lives too ſtrict, their reſpect too great, their main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance too burdenſome, their gifts too eminent, their preaching too oppoſite to libertie of Conſcience, publique exerciſe of every ones gifts, or the like, ſure I am 'tis ſelf that is the Enemy (I write not theſe things with a bitter, but a bleeding heart.)</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. And in the publique Cauſe of reformation. In the mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging 1. of the wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Let us take a ſorrowfull view of the neglect of the things of <hi>Ieſus</hi> in this preſent <hi>Cauſe of Reformation,</hi> and that will plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare alſo to ariſe <hi>from ſeeking theſe owne things;</hi> What if not ſelf-ſeeking hath ſpun us ſuch alaſting thread of calamities, and made our woes ſo long lived, not to ſpeake of the hurt it hath done by the profeſſed oppoſers of Religion, whom it makes little
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:112931:18"/>better then devils in fleſh and blood, though to ſpeak only of theſe would haply more pleaſe us (men commonly taking honey onely out of the carkaſſe of the dead Lyon, and delighting onely in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofes that meddle not with themſelves.) 'Tis ſelf-ſeeking that hath not been onely the <hi>dreyner</hi> of our treaſures, but the <hi>Leech</hi> that hath ſuckt not the bad, but even the beſt blood out of Engliſh veines, the <hi>Moth</hi> that hath <hi>ſo ſtilly</hi> deſtroyed us, the <hi>rotten tooth,</hi> the <hi>broken ſtile of a</hi> poore abuſed nation; <hi>ſelf-ſeeking</hi> hath betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our Cities, Forts, Magazines, Armies, 'tis this that hath made a <hi>trad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of our miſeries,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mercatur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manarum cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatum.</note> that hath made Commanders over places of greateſt Concernment cowardous and treacherous, I, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſomtime hath connived at them too; 'Tis this that hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed our Counſells, and retarded our Expeditions, coveting for <hi>ſelf,</hi> revenging for <hi>ſelf,</hi> ambition for <hi>ſelf</hi> have done theſe things, and thereby undone us. Are there not among us thoſe to be found that deſire to keep our flames ſtill unquenched,<note place="margin">Neſcio quo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ex plicabil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mode fit ut quiſquis ſe ipſum, non Deum amet, non ſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met; &amp; quiſquis Deum non ſe amet, ipſevere ſe amet. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </note> that ſo in ſtead of putting out the fire, they may in a common confuſion ſteale the goods out of the houſe for enriching of ſelves? If <hi>England</hi> be buried, may not this be written on her tombe, <hi>Self-ſeeking hath laid her here;</hi> 'Tis no wonder that God hath <hi>ſought</hi> us no more, that have <hi>ſought him ſo little;</hi> had wee ſought him, and not out ſelves, wee might have found him and our ſelves, but ſeeking our ſelves and not him, we loſe both; <hi>if ſeeking of Chriſt</hi> had beene here, <hi>England</hi> had <hi>not dyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But haply ſelf-ſeeking hath leſſe <hi>neglected Chriſts things,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the <hi>Church;</hi> but here alas I muſt not renew,<note place="margin">In redreſſing the abuſes of the Church.</note> but redouble my complaints; This monſter hath aimed moſtly at the hindering the things <hi>of Chriſt</hi> in that and all it's malice to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, was but in a manner in reference to the Church: what but <hi>ſelf-ſeeking</hi> hath retarded the <hi>Churches</hi> Reformation? the which if advanced, would be ſo great a burden to malignant <hi>ſelf</hi> in ſome, licentious <hi>ſelf</hi> in others; to whom killing confuſion is more welcome then healing order, and all that ſelf might enjoy a latitude, not <hi>of Conſcience</hi> but of ſinning, like little children that are glad their mother is ſick, that ſo they might play without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troulment, 'Tis ſeeking our own things that oppoſeth a ſetling of Government, not withſtanding the ſtudies, and prayers, and tears,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:112931:19"/>not withſtanding the learned and cleare Convictions, which the godly and Orthodox Divines have expreſſed. 'Tis this which (yet) doth cavill away our peace and holineſſe, our order, refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and power of godlineſſe, and threatneth a neceſſitie, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more wofull or wicked (God knoweth) of bearing with all religions. What is it but <hi>ſelf-ſeeking,</hi> which makes us who (in my young remembrance) could weepe, and faſt, and ſeeke God againſt the feares of a toleration of Poperie, now to thinke that it may wel be endured, if ſeparated from tyranny and treaſon againſt the State? This it is that would make <hi>Covenanting with God,</hi> which the godly in all ages uſed as a meanes to pacifio his wrath, and work reformation of life, a meer politick <hi>Character,</hi> onely to put a difference betweene our owne private friends and foes. What but this <hi>ſelf-ſeeking</hi> lies at the bottome of all thoſe (dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſome, diſtracting other) new opiniós with which the Church of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ſo peſtered? what but this founded and <hi>planted</hi> them? what but this favoureth and watereth them? did not ſeeking of <hi>ſelf reputation and gaine</hi> (which could never have been attained by preaching or printing,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.3.</note> good honeſt old Scripture truths in a giddie age) put the Founders of theſe opinions upon the firſt contriving of them? and ſince can it be any thing els but the ſeeking praiſe of men more then the praiſe of God that makes the furtherers to countenance them more then a godly Miniſter, who when hee preacheth them downe is not onely lookt upon with neglect,<note place="margin">3. Self-ſeeking hath hindered the things of Chriſt. In his ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> but with the ſuſpect of Semi-Malignancie? Tell mee now, are the things of Chriſt in the Cauſe of Reformation beholding to ſelf-ſeeking?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the things of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt in his Ordinances</hi> have been infinitely neglected,<note place="margin">1. In his word. 1. It making Miniſters to neglect the word.</note> by <hi>ſeeking theſe own things.</hi> Firſt, <hi>Miniſters</hi> have neglected the Word, as well as people; and all through <hi>ſelf-ſeeking.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For Miniſters: They have heretofore neglected the preaching of the Word,<note place="margin">Tot quotidie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimus quot ad gebe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nam, &amp;c. <hi>Greg. By ſinfull feare.</hi>
               </note> and by their ſinfull ſilence, murthered thouſands of ſoules, But was not <hi>ſelf-ſeeking the cauſe of ſelf-ſilencing?</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time <hi>ſelf</hi> fearing to preach too oft, for diſpleaſing the <hi>reverend Father, or his Grace;</hi> (holding of ones peace, being then the ſtrongeſt, though the baſeſt tenure of holding ones living by;)
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:112931:19"/>Sometime <hi>ſelf ſeeking</hi> hath cauſed <hi>ſelf-ſilencing,</hi> by a wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed neceſſity of <hi>non-reſidencie;</hi> (more places then one,<note place="margin">Hoskins: ſ. Tenu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe ſilentia clerum? <hi>By ſinfull non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiding.</hi> Inveniar ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>varus, adulter, homici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, antipapa &amp; omuium vitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum reus, modo impii ſilemii non arguar. <hi>Luth. ad Staup.</hi> Ut praeſint, non ut proſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt. Piſcatores de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum, non ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum. An non limina Apoſtolorion plus ambitio quam devotio terit? <hi>Bern.</hi> In vit. <hi>Bonif. 3.</hi> Quaeritur quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Epiſcopatus reddat, non quot ſint oves. <hi>Plat.</hi>
               </note> requiring preſence at the ſame time,) when 'twas ſaid that Miniſters labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red more to fiſh for <hi>tithes,</hi> then for <hi>ſoules;</hi> and hence principally thoſe termes of diſgrace in their ſeverall times, were caſt upon them: As <hi>peculatores, non ſpeculatores,</hi> robbers, not watchmen; <hi>praedatores, non praedicatores,</hi> theeves, not teachers: This kinde of <hi>ſelf-ſeeking,</hi> made <hi>Bernard</hi> cnmplain in his time, That more <hi>am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition</hi> then <hi>devotion,</hi> employed thoſe that ſhould have been moſt carefull of the Church; and <hi>Platina</hi> to ſay, That they were wont onely to enquire how many pounds they might get, not how many perſons they might teach. Theſe men checked ſufficiently by the very<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> name of their Office; and this abuſe by Pluralities, as ſeverely reproved by many learned Papiſts, nay oppoſed even to eagerneſſe, in the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> is in part redreſſed, and the reformation thereof will bee much furthered, when Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priations (the more wealthy theeveries of the two, and as ſome think, the onely ſinne eſtabliſht by a Law) ſhall bee ſuppreſſed; the neglect of the Word, by the want of which reformation deſerving to bee thought with the neglecting of it by Pluralities, to ſpring from the ſame root of <hi>ſelf-ſeeking.</hi> Nor hath <hi>ſelf-ſeeking</hi> cauſed timerous ones, and pluraliſts, to neglect the word of Chriſt, but thoſe alſo whom it puts upon the Miniſtery for ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler gains; handfuls of barley, and peeces of bread, though their palpable inſufficiencie makes them as unfit for one place, as the other were for two or three; theſe make the Word the ſcorn of prophane ones, and keep it as a ſealed book from the ignorant ones: If theſe can ſtartle ſome well meaning people into an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of them, or into a contribution to them,<note place="margin">By entrance upon the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery ungifted.</note> they never care for <hi>informing their underſtandings, by principling and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them in the fundamentalls of Religion,</hi> but raiſing by loud voices, and ſtrange geſtures, wonderment and paſſion in their hearers, leave theſe poor ignorant ſoules as a prey to the ſubtill adverſary, who taking advantage by their preſent tenderneſſe and affrightments, (as <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> deſtroyed the <hi>Shechemites</hi> when they were ſore) abuſe and ſeduce them into wayes of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and ſchiſme, the blinde guide meane while, who was fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:112931:20"/>formerly, no man knew why, is now left no man knows how.<note place="margin">By corrupting the word with p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>auſibility of e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>preſſion.</note> At other times <hi>ſelf-ſeeking</hi> hath made the Word ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r by Miniſters, through their corrupting and depraving of it, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time with the mixtures of a trifling wittineſſe, and an empty neatneſſe of phraſe, though commonly ſavouring of as little learning, as edification; they yet ſeeking rather hereby to pleaſe a few ſilly malignants, then to preach <hi>Ieſus Chriſt in power and purity.</hi>
               <note place="margin">I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſit mibi prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> non qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> plauſum ſed qui mibi plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum movet. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ern.</hi>
               </note> What but <hi>ſelf-ſeeking,</hi> hath heretofore turned our <hi>Churches</hi> into <hi>Stages,</hi> and <hi>Preachers</hi> almoſt into <hi>players,</hi> when as the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter</hi> who ſhould onely account the tears, the ſobs, the groans of his hearers his commendations, was wont to ſtop (as at the end of his ſtage) for a <hi>humming</hi> at the cloſe of every point?</p>
            <p>Hath not the Word among us, ſometimes been depraved by <hi>erroneous gloſſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">And with er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations.</note> tortured by <hi>violent interpretations?</hi> how fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently have men made it ſpeak according to their mindes? not bringing their hearts to the Word, but the Word to their hearts; hath not out of the ſweet fountain of truth, the bitter ſtreames of error been made to proceed? are there not ſome who have laboured to turne theſe <hi>waters into bloud,</hi> and to kill thoſe by them, who ſhould have lived in them? Surely 'tis ſo; the moſt prodigious hereſies pretend to a <hi>Scripture,</hi> and the worſt will be wicked <hi>by a Law;</hi> But is there not the hand of <hi>ſelf-ſeeking</hi> in all this? Certainly this it is that hereby to draw many admirers <hi>to ſelf,</hi> cares not how many it withdraws from God, and ſo as it may but be a gainer, cares not though precious ſouls be the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize which it puts off for baſe pelf,<note place="margin">T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. 1.11.</note> for <hi>filthy lucre,</hi> to Satan himſelf.</p>
            <p>But is the Word beholding more to <hi>ſelf-ſeeking</hi> people,<note place="margin">2. Self ſeeking hath made peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple neglect the word, by deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſometimes their preſence at the preaching of it.</note> then to Miniſters? Surely the Word in moſt places can ſcarce bee by them afforded audience: There are ſome who ſay, they are above <hi>Ordinances,</hi> ('twere far better if they were fruitfull un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them) nay that queſtion whether there bee any <hi>Ordinances</hi> or no? and theſe are not called <hi>ſelf-ſeekers,</hi> but <hi>ſeekers;</hi> others that <hi>Hanun-like</hi> have cut off the Word by the middle, the old Teſtament;<note place="margin">By denying the authority of it in their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> and what ever the truth bee, that is urged from that, it is branded with the name of <hi>legall,</hi> which in their ſenſe is as much as <hi>illegall;</hi> and the faithfull reprovers of ſin, and zealous
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:112931:20"/>exhorters to a ſtrict life, are termed but <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> Miniſters; like <hi>Saul,</hi> when <hi>David</hi> was endeavouring to drive away the evill ſpirit with his Harp, they have this javelin, to throw at the faithfull Miniſter, when he is moſt employed in reproving of ſin: others there are that haply give the Word their care, and their pen, and their talk, but 'tis eaſie to ſee how ſlight and ſhallow the impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are, which the Word leaves upon their <hi>conſciences,</hi>
               <note place="margin">By denying the power of it in their lives.</note> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations:</hi> They being like ſome herbes, which Phyſitians tell us are, though hot in the mouth, yet cold in operation; ſo theſe are ſometime holy in their tongues, but heatheniſh in their lives; or like the hill <hi>Etna,</hi> that caſts forth burning coales at the top, but hath at the ſame time froſt and ſnow at the foot thereof; ſo though upon occaſion their words are fiery, yet their lives, their feet, are little better then recantations of the Sermons they hear, the old ſolid <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> the life of <hi>ſelf-deniall, faith and the new creature,</hi> being turn'd into a kinde of ſpruce, ſlight, notionall, out-ſide profeſſion; and there muſt be ſuch a latitude for Chriſtian liberty in diſcourſing, trading, eating, drinking, paſſions, antique habits, that ſome begin to think, people may bee known by theſe things, even to be profeſſors. But what may be the cauſe of this new entertainment of the Word? ſurely this <hi>ſelf</hi> it is that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects more eaſe, a milder, and more indulgent religion, ſuch a latitude as may ſuffice for Chriſt and ſelf too.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> how are they in moſt places almoſt caſt off, and forgotten,<note place="margin">2. Self-ſeeking hath hindered the things of Chriſt in the Sacraments. 1. The Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Supper. In Baptiſme. By abſtaining altogether.</note> and people are very willing to ſtay without them? that of the <hi>Supper</hi> being now accounted an indifferent thing: the ſeldomer <hi>celebrated (Popery hath tackt about we ſee)</hi> the better; and for that other of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> 'tis by ſome eſteemed null, fond, and groundleſſe, who deride, through ignorance, that condeſcenſion of Chriſt which they ſhould praiſe with thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. What? is <hi>ſelf</hi> here too? yes. This proceeds from the ſame root with that, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.21. a love of <hi>diviſion;</hi> from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, an <hi>overweening opinion of our ſelves, and way;</hi> or, an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of <hi>a ſelfe-contrived, and unſcripturall ſanctity,</hi> it being the moſt pleaſing thing in the world to <hi>ſelf,</hi> to have opinions of out own breed, eſpecially if they teach and plead for holineſſe in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; <hi>for men may urge that with much credit, and little coſt;</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:112931:21"/>and that's the reaſon that you ſhall obſerve among people forty diſcourſes of the qualifications of the company they receive withall, for one diſcourſe of the hearts which they themſelves ſhould receive withall.</p>
            <p>Others neglect the Sacrament in the manner of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, not in their keeping away, but in comming with little rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe of ſoule, dead affections, narrow hearts to entertaine a great good,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> not with empty hands to take <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. What's the reaſon? <hi>ſelf-employments</hi> have ſo fill'd and ſtuf't their hearts with traſh, that there's no room for pearls.</p>
            <p>Others come with impure, unclean ſoules; with no ſutable ſanctity to a glorious God, to whoſe entertainment they pretend adventuring like <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> who when he went to meet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> went untrimmed, undreſſed, unwaſhed; ſo theſe receive with dirty, unwaſhen hands, luſtfull, proud, revengefull, covetous hearts: What's the cauſe? they come with the ſame hearts in which they were in their ſelf-proſecutions; they love to go ſo dreſſed, as they may be ever in a readineſſe to ſerve <hi>ſelf.</hi> The wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is to them like <hi>Sauls</hi> armour to <hi>David,</hi> too burdenſome and heavy, too great a hinderance from earthly enquiries.</p>
            <p>I have done with the ſecond Inference, <hi>viz. Self-ſeeking is the cauſe why the things of Chriſt have been neglected among us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A third follows: <hi>Wee ought to endeavour the beating down this ſelf-ſeeking in all our ſouls;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Inference. Direction.</note> this immoderate letting the heart run out in ſelf-ſearches.</p>
            <p>Lay the <hi>foundation</hi> of <hi>mortification</hi> deep,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.19. 1. <hi>Direction.</hi> Lay the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification deep.</note> even deeper then ever was thy delight in thy moſt eagerly proſecuted comforts, not in a meer abſtinence from the uſe of, but in an inward taking off the heart from any thing that may take thee off from Chriſt. There are many who think, if they leave the pleaſure, the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward following this or that ſinfull gaine, or ambitious promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they are mortified ſoules; alas, what's this, as long as the heart is uncleanſed, the affection uncrucified? A man that deſires to ſhun ſickneſſe, muſt not onely be watchfull, in keeping himſelf from the ſharpneſſe of the ayre, but muſt remove the corruption of his ſtomack. If the body be diſtempered, 'twill catch cold with the leaſt blaſt; and ſo an uncleanſed ſoul will be wrought upon by
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:112931:21"/>very temptation. The bird which is tied by the legge with a ſiring to a ſtone,<note place="margin">Non voluptas relinquenda, ſed voluntas depo nenda, non ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcindunt, ſed ab ſcondunt peccata <hi>Tert.</hi> Quando a me ipſo alienabor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> perdam? <hi>Bern.</hi> Revelle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ateipſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ut Deo inſerari divid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> te a teipſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ut cum creatore n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iaris, extirpa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a te peſſimo ut in om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> bono radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceris. Tu qui om nia relinquere diſponis, te qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que inter relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenda numera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e memento. <hi>Bern.</hi> Neſcivit ſuis par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere, quia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> no. it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> perhaps with ſome ſtrugling gets looſe from the ſtone, to which the ſtring on the other end was faſtned, but then flying with the ſtring about her leg, ſhee is entangled in the next bough ſhee flies to, more then before. 'Tis not enough to leave the uſe of this, or that way, or object, unleſſe we ſtrive to pull off the ſtring too, the luſt that tied us. Never bee at quiet as long as there's this <hi>Mordecai</hi> in the gate; entreat God to alienate thee from thy ſelf, to root up ſelf in thee, to annihilate what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſtands up in thy ſoul, in a way of reſiſting Chriſt; though the lot fall even upon <hi>Jonathan,</hi> let him go; Say, Oh that I could looſe my ſelf, to come to Chriſt! Let the motions of ſelf in the ſoule bee thy continuall ſighing; reſerve nothing in it from the ſtroak of Chriſt, for if ſo, proviſion will at length be made for it, even to a forſaking of Chriſt, if occaſion require; <hi>This imperfect aim at ſelf-ſubduing, is the cauſe of ſelf-ſeeking,</hi> and very dangerous are theſe <hi>ſemi-renouncings of ſelf;</hi> If there be any luſt unſubdued, it will plead its intereſt, and often ſo craftily, as there will be no an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering it, carnall will, evermore having carnall wit, and excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to further it; Let not the blade of the luſting bee ſnib'd, but let the root be cut up. If thou would'ſt put out the ſlame, quench the bottom of it: <hi>Levi</hi> kil'd his own neareſt kindred, becauſe he had killed <hi>ſelf</hi> before.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Direction.</hi> Make a right diſcovery of the delights of Chriſt.</note> 
               <hi>Make a right diſcovery of the raviſhing delights, and the ſatisfying benefits which every beleever hath in Ieſus Chriſt, who infinitely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t-bids all that ſelf is ſo eager in proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of.</hi> Behold the comforts of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, in this ſeven-fold diſcovery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. View them as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>all.</note> 
               <hi>View them as realities, not as notions; Self</hi> counts all the things of heaven but empty ſpeculations; A carnall heart ſaith, Look thee here, behold this pleaſure, profit, &amp;c. taſt it, touch it, handle it, be enricht with it; a ſpirit hath nothing for thy body, thy life, &amp;c. for your good things of heaven, they have nothing but empty names; what talk you of the life of faith? you might beg if 'twere not for your land. When <hi>Moſes</hi> was in the Mount,<note place="margin">Exod. 32.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and the Iſraelites knew not what was become of him, then they
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:112931:22"/>made golden gods; and thus it is with carnall hearts, they know not what's become of heaven, and Chriſt; they think they are loſt and gon things, and that there's nothing in them, and then's the time to make gold, and pleaſure, and honour our gods. Therefore,<note place="margin">2 Cor 4 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> O Chriſtian, look upon the things of eternity, as reall, certaine things; <hi>not opinions, but aſſertions.</hi> The Apoſtle ſpeaks of things, <hi>that are not ſeen;</hi> yet mark, he ſaith, <hi>for all that, wee looke at theſe things.</hi> They are not <hi>imaginary,</hi> becauſe <hi>inviſible;</hi> look upon them,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.34. Heb. 11.1.</note> as being <hi>a ſubſtance;</hi> for ſo they are denoted, more then once, in the Scripture. I know not how it comes to paſſe, but theſe things of <hi>ſelf-enquiry</hi> have ſtoln away the name of <hi>ſubſtance</hi> from Chriſts things; mens goods are called <hi>their ſubſtance;</hi> a wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ldly rich man, is cal'd a ſubſtantiall man, &amp;c. where as all theſe things below,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.36.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Per falla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia bona nurad vera mala per fallacia mala ad vera bona. <hi>Lactant.</hi> Potius ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus quam diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimus de coe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o.</note> are but ſhadows, and have onely ſo much of <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> as they have of Chriſt in them. Hitherto you have asked nothing, ſaith Chriſt, though they had asked ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and wealth. That <hi>which is not,</hi> the Wiſe-man calls them: Therefore when <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpeaks of himſelf, and his own things, he calls them, <hi>things indeed,</hi> as if other things were but <hi>phantaſticall;</hi> but here's the miſery, wee ſpeake of the things of Chriſt, as dreames and ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>culations; and that's the reaſon, when ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, as wee think, more certaine comes in the way, our hearts are gone.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2. View them a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> abundant.</hi> Gaudtum eſt ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>entium quoddam appetitus, epulum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ordis, mors deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derit. Pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tum eſt quiesa volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> View the <hi>comforts of Chriſt, as full, abundant,</hi> not as ſcanty, ſutable to <hi>all thy exigencies,</hi> ſo that <hi>thou needeſt not goe to any thing here below, to eek them out withall;</hi> they are ſuch full things, that they want nothing but wants, and thirſtings after them. View them, as able to ſatisfie all thy longings, to quiet thy wiſhes, to ſilence thy deſires, to kill thy hunger; able to fill thy ſoule,<note place="margin">Auguſta Dei bonitas ſun ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i Chriſtus. Sola in integritate di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bonitatis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſatiare po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt apperitus.</note> like the Water-pots of <hi>Galilee,</hi> up to the brim; no ſatisfaction but from theſe comforts. The ſoul can never ſay, it hath enough, till it hath an intereſt in them. <hi>It is enough,</hi> ſaid old <hi>Iacob, Ioſeph my ſonne is yet alive.</hi> It is enough, may that ſoul ſay in whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> liveth, for whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> died; enough though God ſhould give me no more; enough honour, though I ſhould alway be in diſgrace; enough ſtrength, though my body
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:112931:22"/>bee weak; enough riches, though I bee otherwiſe in poverty; there's ſo much of all good in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Omnium incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationum quibus res ad ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> centus proru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt, debitra re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> te exiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imeo-Fortior ſit gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. tia quam natura-Omnes diſperſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes inclinatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, omnes erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>piditatum in te congregare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ram in Deum conten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as. <hi>Ioh. Euſ. Nier.</hi>
               </note> that the ſoule owes him all the inclinations, and propenſities by which all the things in the world are with greateſt vehemencie carried to their ſeverall <hi>obiects, centers,</hi> and <hi>reſts.</hi> A Chriſtian ſhould labour to gather to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether all his diſperſed and ſcattered deſires, that have run out upon other by-comforts, and fix them alone upon <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> who hath the ſweetneſſe, and the deſirableneſſe of them all within himſelf; there's ſo much in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> that the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance that one Saint receives, can be no cauſe of repining in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; there's <hi>vera</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo much plenty, that it baniſheth envie, Chriſt is a <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> a well of plenty and ſatisfaction for all his Saints; our veſſels will ſooner be wanting then his oyle.</p>
            <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3. View them as perci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us, not as vile.</hi> De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it ſe de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dmine genera ſitatis qui admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quid poſt D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um poteſt. <hi>Cypr de ſpee.</hi> Ethrici reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querum mun dum. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Omnium rerum colliquata vonuſtas ad divinam pulchritudirem comparata ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> mundus amat crux mibi ſunt, quae mundus reput<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ucent illis affixus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um toto affect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Bern.</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hunc mundum tuguriolum Adami, crgaſtulum pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>atorum, ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>am brutorum, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am adminabi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Deus, quid erit d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mus propria &amp; a al Dei?</note> View them as <hi>precious, ſublime,</hi> and <hi>excellent,</hi> not as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and droſſie. This will heighten thy ſoule, and put an h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly generoſity into it, and make thee count the beautifulleſt things that <hi>ſelf</hi> admires, unworthy thy ſtoop, as <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> who did bid a poor man ſtanding by him, take up a pearl that lay upon the ground, for thou (ſaid he) art not <hi>Themiſtocles.</hi> Hee that looks earneſtly upon the Sunne, will have his eyes ſo dazled, that hee can ſee nothing upon the ſudden. Let the eye of thy ſaith be hold the beauties of eternity, and then other things will not bee coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted worthy thy regard; there will be in thee a holy neglective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of them: Thou wilt ſay to thy ſelf of the moſt glorious buildings, and ſumptuous palaces upon earth, as Chriſt, upon occaſion of his Diſciples admiration, of the Temples ſtructure; Are theſe the things thou lookeſt upon?</p>
            <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">4. View them a uſefull, not as idle and unh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.</note> View them as <hi>uſefull,</hi> and <hi>efficacious,</hi> not as <hi>idle,</hi> and <hi>unhelping;</hi> Even in thy ſaddeſt houres, able to comfort thee; in thy poverty, to enrich thee; in thy doubts, to direct thee; in thy ſtraights, to enlarge thee: It is therefore by ſome thought, that the <hi>pleaſures</hi> of the Saints in Scripture, are ſaid to be at Gods <hi>right hand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Organon roboris</note> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the ſtrength and power (that being the embleme of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:112931:23"/>ſtrength) which God beſtowes upon them, to relieve and uphold their ſoules.<note place="margin">Pſal. 16. ult.</note> The benefits that God in Chriſt beſtowes, are not ſuch as wee uphold, but ſuch as uphold us: the comforts of eternity are living waters; quick, and quickning, and enlive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning comforts. The conſolations the Apoſtle ſpeaks of are ſtrong conſolations,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.18. Pſal. 119.54.</note> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> ſtrengthening. <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks of ſongs in the houſe of his pilgrimage; when he was farre from friends, they made a ſupply.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant 2.4.</note> The love of Chriſt is ſaid to be a banner, an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, to note the courage, and divine valour, which in apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of it,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am 23.16.</note> a Saint may gather to himſelf. <hi>Ionathan</hi> ſtrengthened <hi>Davids</hi> hand, and ſo doth Chriſt his peoples. <hi>David</hi> comforted <hi>himſelf in his God.</hi> Look upon Chriſt, as able to ſuſtain thee, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting thy ſelf upon him, though all creature crutches were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved.</p>
            <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">5. View them as thoſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou haſt a propriety not as anothers.</note> 
               <hi>Look upon them, as things wherein thou haſt a propriety, not as an others onely.</hi> Vnite, apply, appropriate the benefits of Chriſt to thine own ſoul. A man that views never ſo much land, or wealth, if he have not an intereſt therein, will not be thereby ſtopt in his poorer enquiries, and deſires. Chriſt is never good in a ſouls account, till it hath ſomething of him; and the more it hath of him, the leſſe it ſeeks in any thing elſe beſide him. 'Tis the owning of Chriſt, and taking him as <hi>thine,</hi> that will make thee contented, when thou ſeeſt that nothing is thine elſe; 'tis onely this which can take thee off from earthly-proſecutions. In one Chriſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.5.</note> is comprized every ſcattered comfort here below. Chriſt mine, ſaith the ſoule, and all mine. An union to Chriſt, eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unites from any thing elſe. The ſoul anſwers the unlawfull offers that the world makes to it of honors, riches, &amp;c. like the conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Shunamite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 4.13.</note> when ſhe had offers of Court courteſies, I dwell with mine own Chriſt, I deſire not to alter my condition; my Chriſt hath all you offer, and much more.</p>
            <p n="6">6.<note place="margin">6. View them as preſent, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> diſtant.</note> 
               <hi>View them as preſent, brought neere;</hi> let thy faith pull them even into thy ſoul: What's the reaſon that the worlds offers pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with us more then Chriſts? the world comes with money in hand, we look upon it as neere, we think that God asks too long day for payment; we look not with the <hi>Proſpective of faith</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the things of heaven, did we ſo, we ſhould ſee them hard by,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:112931:23"/>and a few moneths and yeers would be counted as <hi>Iacobs ſtaying for Rachel</hi> but a very ſhort time; faith would preſent them as at hand, and as their's did them,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.13.</note> would make us to ſalute and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace them ſo, although they ſhould be to ſenſe afarre off; faith even now layes hold on eternall life,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.19.</note> and views the promiſes as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready performed, and therefore <hi>David</hi> even when he was crying,<note place="margin">Pſal. 57.2.</note> and praying, tells us 'twas to that God that <hi>performeth</hi> all things for him, <hi>performeth now.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7.<note place="margin">7. View them as eternall, not as finite.</note> View them as eternall, not as finite; comforts that ſhall tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over time; ſo the word, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. tranſlated (evermore) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth. Time triumpheth and maketh a ſpoile of every thing thou canſt ſeek here upon earth,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> AEternitas q. victoria tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris.</note> but Chriſts things triumph over time; ſo ſhall wee ever be with the Lord, ſaith <hi>Paul.</hi> There will come a time when as Chriſt will not ſay, The poore you have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes with you, and me you have not alwayes; no, me you ſhall have alway, and povertie no longer; joyes alwayes, teares no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; fulneſs alway, hunger no longer; glory alway, ſhame no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: oh ſtudie what 'tis to be for ever with the Lord; <hi>Ever, Ever!</hi> Chriſt hath made an <hi>Act of Continuation</hi> for thy joyes, they ſhall never breake up. The good things of Chriſt are called in Scripture frequently a treaſure; the word ſignifieth ſomething laid up for afterward; Ieſus Chriſt and his benefits are onely the ſame,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and to day, and for ever.</p>
            <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">3. <hi>Direction.</hi>
               </note> I have done with the ſecond Direction to beat downe ſelf-ſearches, which was to take a right view of the benefits of Chriſt, I come to a third. Labour for a ſanctified uſe of <hi>all embitterments or ſtoppages,</hi> in thy eagreſt ſelf-enquiries and proſecutions; when the ſea ſtormed 'twas a ſigne God would have <hi>Ionah</hi> returne to his work, and leave his eager and unlawfull voyage; Doth God raiſe any ſtormes of diſgrace, povertie, ſicknes, in the following this or that luſting? uſe it as ſtoppage in thy courſe; as one ſaid once, <hi>Vix licet vivere &amp; licet fornicari?</hi> I can ſcarce live, and ſhould I be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane, proud, revengefull, ambitious? The heathen could obſerve that when men were ſicke, they would abſtaine from former ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes. Looke upon Gods more bitter diſpenſations, as ſo many meetings of thee in the narrow way, as he did <hi>Balaam</hi> to keepe thee from going on in thy eager proſecutions, ſo many breakings
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:112931:24"/>downe of the bridges to hinder thy paſſage,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> pratere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> uſe holy upbraiding<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of thy ſelf when thou ſuffereſt from God. Tell thy gadding ſoule, thou mayſt thank it for all thy ſorrows; drive home the naile of affliction further by the ſelf-crucifying hand. Thinke with thy ſelfe when God makes the things of the world to leave thee, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did his Miſtris when ſhe would have plaid the Adultereſſe; that Gods aime is, thou ſhouldeſt not commit ſpirituall adulterie with the gifts of God, which he onely gave thee for thy ſervants.</p>
            <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">4. <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ction.</hi> Moder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> A holy moderating of thy luſting out-running heart, in the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers and enjoyments <hi>of thoſe lawfull</hi> objects with which thy luſts have been moſt taken. Fire the ſhips if thou wouldſt not be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away by them, be watchfull and moderate in lawfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, uſe them with a godly jealouſie; deny thy ſelf much even of that which poſſibly thou mayſt uſe well, engulph not thy ſelfe in pleaſure, employments, profits. A ſhip in the mud is lanched forth with difficultie; ſo is a mans heart allowing himſelfe boldly abundance of outward comforts, with difficultie carried off to the employments of Chriſt from ſelf-attendances. A man ſhould in this caſe even <hi>ſtop up the wells,</hi> as they did when they would doe the enemies a diſcourteſie,<note place="margin">1 King. 3.19.</note> and marre every <hi>good peece of ground,</hi> every naturally bewitching object with a ſober heedfull ſparing enjoyment of it,<note place="margin">Chriſtian liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e eaſily grows <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o unchriſtian I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bertiniſm.</note> pare off ſuperfluities and abundance, ſet this task<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter of warines over thy gadding idle ſoule; <hi>Make not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, Rom.</hi> 13.14. for the fleſh. Let not thy ſoule be (as a candle in a ſtinking filthy lanthorn) in a body wallowing in ſenſuall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; uſe the things of the world as <hi>Gideons ſouldiers</hi> drank thoſe waters, not ſtooping downe to them, and lying along, but out of the palmes of their hands;<note place="margin">Sint ſolatia, non negotia. <hi>Dent. 25.3.</hi>
               </note> let theſe things be thy refreſhments, not thy buſineſſes; let not thy life be the life of a Muſhrum, as if thou hadſt no other ſoule but a <hi>vegetative;</hi> ever be willing to deny thy ſelfe ſom what of that thou mayſt doe or enjoy, as the Iewes in puniſhing Malefactors, were allowed to <hi>give fourtie ſtripes,</hi> but they gave but 39. ſo let thy care be to cut thy ſelfe ſhort in many things thou mayſt doe.</p>
            <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">5. <hi>Direction.</hi> A deare love to Ieſus Chriſt.</note> A <hi>deare love to Ieſus Chriſt; praedominant over all other:</hi> Love thy ſelfe onely in Chriſt, and theſe things onely as they are beſtowed upon thee as pledges of his love; As thou canſt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:112931:24"/>not pleaſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> by any out-ſide performances thou giveſt him,<note place="margin">Quaedam a ſe peregrinati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, mors voluntaria. <hi>Ioſ. Nie. de arte vol.</hi> Si iſta terrena diligitis ut ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecta diligate, ut munera amici, ut beneficia Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni ut arrham ſponſi. <hi>Aug. med.</hi> Occurrit aliquid amoenum? ſtatim valadum clypeum oppone Chriſtum. Quale hoc in s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onſo meo erit! nolo occupari in hac mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a venu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatis, in hoc ato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo duleoris, ſed totam amoenita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem hauriam in Deo, ita praevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabere appetitus his veneno, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia bona Phyla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteria tua ſunt, ut Deum ames &amp; nihil adores aliud.</note> unleſſe thou giveſt thy ſelfe; ſo neither let him pleaſe thee, unleſſe he gives thee <hi>himſelf,</hi> though he beſtows the world in never ſuch abundance. Delight not in theſe things, nor deſire them further then as they may either be ſeen to <hi>proceed from a loving Saviour, or returned unto him.</hi> If thy love were principally ſet upon Chriſt, thou wouldeſt onely regard theſe things as they are tokens of his love, as mercies not as gifts; without his love they would be as a ceale without fire in it, all dark and black and uncomfortable any further then thou didſt ſee <hi>Chriſt</hi> in them; If any thing ſweet and amiable preſented it ſelfe to thee, thou wouldeſt preſently ſay and think, Oh what is there in my beloved if there be ſo much in theſe things! I wil not be employed in a drop, in an atom of ſweetneſſe, but be raiſed up in my thoughts, and be infinitely taken with him that is the <hi>fountaine of all love and lovelines;</hi> theſe things below would not <hi>fallere,</hi> but <hi>monere;</hi> not be witch thee from him, but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh thee of and to him, they would be ſo many ſteps to raiſe up thy ſoule more to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> they would be but Phylacteries to make thee mindful of his wil and pleaſure in them, and no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wouldſt thou be rejoyced in the enjoyment of them, then that thou might'ſt be ſerviceable to Chriſt by them.</p>
            <p n="6">6.<note place="margin">6. <hi>Direction.</hi> Occaſion of the enquiries from ſelf and earth. Pſal. 119.36. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mper tentator te inveniat occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patum.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> Occaſion of thy enquiries from ſelf and earth, by ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much time in heavenly ſervices and employments, praying, reading, hearing, meditating. <hi>Otioſus verſatur in deſideriis,</hi> idle perſons are craving oft, <hi>Pro.</hi> 13.4. Tell thy luſtings when they ſolicite thee, thou art otherwiſe buſied. Let the tempter never finde thee idle; empty table books may have any thing written in them, if fild before, the writer is prevented; let Satan finde thy ſoule fild ever with ſomething of Ieſus Chriſt, if thou wouldſt ſhun Satans temptation to luſtings.</p>
            <p n="7">7.<note place="margin">7. Encreaſe of acquaintance vvith Ieſus Chriſt.</note> Labour daily to encreaſe <hi>thy humble and ſweet familiaritie</hi> with <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> never ſtand at a ſtay in taking in his comforts, labour to have them come in freſh every morning, endeavour that thy flame of loves and deſires may daily bee ſupplied with freſh fuell, pleaſe not thy ſelfe in any degrees of his <hi>comforts, grace, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtations;</hi> if thou do'ſt, he will ſoon grow leſſe deſirable to thee and them, thou wilt goe elſ-where for refreſhments. Chriſt hath
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:112931:25"/>war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ety of bleſſed employments, flie from flower to flower, rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing in the varietie of his precious promiſes, deceive thy <hi>nauſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting nature with</hi> intermixing one holy ſervice with another, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time heare, other while pray, frequently meditate, be not ſeldome in godly company; Chriſt this way will with more delight take thee up from ſelf employments; when thy luſtings ſolicite thee to this or that object, ask thy ſoule the queſtion that the Prophet did <hi>Ahaziahs</hi> meſſengers;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> King. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Is there not a God in <hi>Jſrael,</hi> that thou ſhouldſt go to <hi>Baal-z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bub the God of Ekron?</hi> Is there never a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe in the Scripture? never a Saint of my acquaintance? never a mercie to be thankfull for? never a luſt to be ſtriving with? no beautie and glory in heaven to be panting after?</p>
            <p>I have done with the third Inference, which was that wee ought to endeavour the remoovall of ſelf-ſeeking out of our ſoules.</p>
            <p>A fourth and the laſt follows.</p>
            <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">4. Interenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Wee ſhould be diſſwaded from the ſeeking our owne things, whereby the things of Chriſt are ſo neglected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall urge this Dehortation upon a two-fold conſideration, both taken out of the Text.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Be dehorted from theſe <hi>inordinate ſearches,</hi> by conſidering upon <hi>what ground</hi> and reaſon men take them up; 'tis upon this ground: They look upon the things they ſeek and follow as their <hi>owne things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. By conſidering whoſe the things are that will be neglected thereby, even <hi>the things of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That which puts us upon the eager attendance upon theſe things, is the accounting them our owne things.</p>
            <p>Now in this firſt conſideration, <hi>viz.</hi> the ground of peoples ſearch, there be three notable diſſwaſions to take us off from ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe things, upon that ground that they are our owne.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The falſneſs and deceitfulneſs of a ſearch and enquirie upon that ground.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The lowneſs and the unworthineſs of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Our liableneſs and readineſs to be overtaken by it, and to offend in it.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:112931:25"/>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, upon what ground men ſeeke theſe things, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe they are their own containing a 3. fold diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion. 1. The deceit of this ground, theſe things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not our own in a 3. fold reſpect not our owne. Luke 16.12. Hab. 2.6.</note> To ſeek other things beſide the things of Ieſus Chriſt as our own, is to be falſe to our ſelves, to deceive our ſelves, (ſelf-ſeeking is ſelf-deceiving in this reſpect) for they are not our owne, they want that for the which we ſo eagerly proſecutE them; <hi>Iſaac be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing blind, demanded of Iacob</hi> who came to him for the Bleſſing, whether he was his very ſonne <hi>Eſan,</hi> or no; had hee not thought that he had been ſo, hee would not have bleſt him; did not people think that theſe things below were their very owne, they would never beſtow their regards upon them as they do; upon that foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation they ſet up the building of all their proſecutions, but alas! what a ſlender ſandy foundation is it? the Scripture tells us they are not our owne.</p>
            <p>Here's ſelf-deceit, when we account them our own, in a three-fold reſpect.</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. They are not our ſouls, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not our own.</note> They are not <hi>our ſouls things, and therefore not our own things,</hi> they are thy carkaſſes not thy ſoules, thy purſes, thy ſhops, thy cheſts, not thy ſoules.</p>
            <p>They are not proportioned in reſpect <hi>of abundance,</hi> or largeneſs to thy capacious ſoul, the whole world is not to thy ſoul ſo much as a drop to the belly of an Elephant;<note place="margin">1. Not large enough for the ſoule. <hi>Concija bonitas creaturam quae mutatio noſtri generis, ut ſolam divinitat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am faſtidiat. Cupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditas noſtra <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melica omnium niſs e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us in quo ſolo ſatiart po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt.</hi>
               </note> All fulnes that is not my God (ſaith one) is nothing but emptines; all that is not Ieſus Chriſt is curt and penurious, and ſcantie; they are not able all put together to throw in one mite into the treaſurie of the ſoule. <hi>Hagar</hi> when ſhee was out of <hi>Abrahams</hi> houſe, inſtantly found povertie, and ſoon was her bottle of water ſpent, and ſo all earthly comforts afford no ſupply out of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. Not good enough for the ſoule. <hi>Opprobria hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manae naturae.</hi> Gen. 2.20.</note> They are not proportioned in worth for the ſoule, they are meane and droſſie; they are not a match fit for thy ſoule: It againe may be ſaid of all the Creation as 'twas once upon another occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Among all the creatures there was not found an help meet, &amp;c.</hi> Among all the things here below there's not to be found a meet companion for the ſoule; ther's no food here below that thy ſoule loves, no cloathing to cover thy ſoule, no coyne to enrich thy ſoule, no habitation to entertaine thy ſoule; they are all below it of another kinde. Thy ſoule when it becomes a ſeeker of theſe things, is like the excellent trees that went to the bramble to be their King.<note place="margin">Iudg. 9.14.15.</note> Theſe things below that thou ſetteſt the enquiries of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:112931:26"/>thy ſoule moſt upon deſerve more that the <hi>tramplings of thy feet ſhould be upon them;</hi> there's no more preciouſnes in them then what thy opinion impoſeth upon them.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. They are not uſefull, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not our own. <hi>Amor infirmi robar miſeriae.</hi> Pro. 11.4. <hi>Nec plenitadi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem continenti, nec <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> inmt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nsi prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent.</hi>
               </note> They are not thine in reſpect <hi>of uſefulnes,</hi> when thou ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in greateſt need of them; <hi>adverſity will try what they things are,</hi> they are then but <hi>broken ſtilts;</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Theſe <hi>Baals cannot plead for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> if either fire, or theeves, or ſickneſſe, or loſſes ſeiſe upon them, how then ſhould they plead for thee? There's nothing that thou here truſteſt in, but like <hi>Micha's gods</hi> may be ſtolen away; poor gods that cannot defend themſelves.</p>
            <p>Theſe things profit not in the day of Wrath; wee may expect much from them, but when any come to uſe them, they are like quagmires that ſhew green, and ſeem to be hard, but when thou goeſt to tread upon them they will not beare thy weight.</p>
            <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3. Not things that will ſtand by us, therefore not our own.</hi> Impatientia amoris noſtri. Quid mag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t agam ſi re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam pro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e rem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>em quae propter ſe, aut propter me re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenda eſſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Mat. 6.20.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Tantum quiſque valet quantum am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. Quiequid amico accidit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ibi acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</note> 
               <hi>They are not things that will ſtay with us,</hi> therefore not our owne, <hi>they are like</hi> lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eph <hi>when his Miſtris laid hold upon him, be gave her the ſlip This night</hi> ſaid God to the rich fool <hi>ſhall thy ſoule be taken from thee, and then</hi> whoſe ſhall theſe things be that thou reckoneſt upon? All creature comforts are like thoſe enemies of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that <hi>paſſed by him</hi> when he was upon the croſſe, all tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie; the faſhion of this word paſſeth away, periſhing comforts ſhould be proſecuted with a periſhing love, and a vaniſhing affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; not as the things for which we doe live, but as the things in this ſtate, without which we cannot altogether live. Chriſt tels us <hi>of a moth</hi> that eats into all earthy treaſures; <hi>Child, and land, and beautie, nay life, have their moth.</hi> The ſweeteſt comforts like the Roſe wither ſooneſt, they are all like poore or deceitfull traders, they will break ſooner or later, and then what will become of thee that haſt lent them, nay beſtowed upon them thy loves and affections, which are all thou art worth? if they breake thou muſt needs loſe too: there's nothing hereto be loved, but as if thou wert alwayes about to leave it,<note place="margin">Ama tanquam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> nay to loath it if God require; there's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing here below dyed in graine, all their ſweetnes and beautie will ſoon weare and waſh out.</p>
            <p>There's the firſt diſſwaſion in the firſt Conſideration, the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of this principle, that they are our own.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond diſſwaſion in the firſt Conſideration, <hi>viz. that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:112931:26"/>they are ſought, becauſe our own is the vilenes an unworthines of this principle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2. Diſſwaſion. Vnworthineſſe of this temper in reſpect of private ſpirited<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Matth. 6.32.</hi> Diſce perire ut vivat Chriſti gloria. Mallet pro aliis occidi quam ſibi v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vere. <hi>Amb. in obit. Satyri.</hi> Aliquid habui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ui Chriſtum praeferrepotu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Moſes cauſam populi apud De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ibus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amſi cauſam Dei apud popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum glad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is all<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it. <hi>Greg. Mot.</hi> Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aliquando quod ſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eliciſſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus fueris fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> us e; in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> It argues an unworthy unchriſtian temper, for a man to lay out his proſecutions upon his owne private employments, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely below a true Saintlike ſoule; 'tis much below the end of a Saint, onely to ſeeke the ſalvation though of his <hi>owne</hi> ſoule, but to regard <hi>theſe owne things of</hi> the body, <hi>Chriſt</hi> tells us 'tis the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition <hi>of a heathen;</hi> the advancing of <hi>Chriſts</hi> name in the world muſt be our ſcope; the making him famous, our work; our deſire muſt be onely to be conduits of Chriſts favours, to be ſtewards of his goods, to lay out our very ſelves in his praiſe, unſerviceablenes muſt be a Saints greateſt burden. The excellencie of a pillar is not beautie, but ſervice and uſefulnes in bearing up the building, and ſo 'tis with a Saint; his excellencie ſtands not in wealth, in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours &amp;c. but bearing up the glory and cauſe <hi>of Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> not to live for himſelfe, but even to die for the Publique if God ſhould call for it; the glorie of a Saint is to have had ſomewhat to which he hath preferred, or may preferre Ieſus Chriſt, to ſet up Chriſt a building of glory though upon his own ruines.</p>
            <p>The moſt famous Saints in the world were made ſo <hi>by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique ſpiritednes;</hi> how glorious will <hi>Moſes</hi> be to poſteritie, that he was not willing to be happie alone either in <hi>Pharaohs Court</hi> or <hi>Gods favour:</hi> ſo <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> with the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt, they were all made noble by this being above their owne things; Oh what a vile temper is it for a Chriſtian to be himſelf the Center of his owne ends, and the gulfe of his owne comforts? Caſt (ſaith Chriſt) that unprofitable <hi>ſervant into utter darknes,</hi> &amp; then there's <hi>gurges in gurgite,</hi> one gulfe in another; how unlike is this temper to that of the Saints in heaven, who have no other worke but to ſing the praiſes of Chriſt to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ternitie?</p>
            <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">3. Diſſwaſion in the firſt Conſideration. Our liablenes to offend in ſeeking our owne things, &amp; that in a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold regard.</note> A third diſſwaſion in the firſt Conſideration is this; As there is much lowneſs and unworthineſs in ſeeking our own, ſo there is much readines in us to offend God in ſeeking them. 'Tis infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly difficult not to miſcarry in following theſe own things, and that</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Jn regard, following our own is a lawfull liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Offences in following our own things, ſeldom are reproved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>We are infinitly, &amp; eager, and vehement in proſecutions for ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:112931:27"/>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. The ſeeking our own things, is in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ort law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are ready to offend therein. Iob 1.</note> We are liable to offend God in following our owne things, becauſe the ſeeking of them is in a ſort allowed by God as lawfull. <hi>Satan</hi> commonly puts off his bad wares of ſin among theſe good ones, <hi>lawfull things; as Satan came</hi> in among the ſons of God, ſo commonly ſinne comes in in employments in their owne natures lawfull enough; Poyſon is not given to any under that notion, but under the notion of good food &amp; wholeſom diet, and ſo it is taken unſuſpectedly. <hi>It's eaſie to ſinne in lawfull things,</hi> to ſeeke ſinfully our ſelves, immoderately, regardleſly of God or his Church, when God allows to ſeek at all; though indeed Gods gracious permiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on herein ſhould rather make us more free in his ſervice, then full in our own, and be rather a bond of obedience, then a ſnare of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. The old world was firſt drowned in the abuſe of lawfull pleaſures and profits, before 'twas drowned with water: <hi>They did eat and drinke, they married, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 24.38.</note> 'Twas <hi>the abuſe of lawfull things, buying and ſelling, &amp;c. that kept</hi> them <hi>from the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per;</hi> ſo 1 Cor. 10.7.<note place="margin">Luke 14.16.</note> 
               <hi>We ſee what the people offended in, they ſat down to eat and drink, and roſe up to play.</hi> Food, apparell, acquaintance, marriage, callings, recreations all lawfull, and doe not thouſands miſcarry in the ſinfull uſing of them? Satan commonly lyeth in ambuſh againſt out ſoules, behind our lawfull liberties. Things lawfully gotten, are moſt commonly unlawfully affected.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. Difficultie of diſcovery by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry liable to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend in them.</note> Others cannot eaſily diſcover it in us, or reprove and taxus for theſe ſearches, they may thinke perhaps 'tis needfull proviſion for family, wife, children, health, ſupportation of rank, and place, when yet our hearts are immoderately bent upon our ſelf-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions; we are not noted for any ſcandalous faults; as unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſwearing, ſabbath-breaking, &amp;c. and therefore haply o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may have a good opinion of us in the midſt of our <hi>moſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſelf-ſeeking,</hi> hence the <hi>condition of a ſelf-ſeeker is worſe then of one more openly prophane,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſt tale mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum quod eſt ſimpliciter im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peccab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e. <hi>Luth.</hi> Vbi non timetur reprebenſor faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius accedit tentator. <hi>Greg. Luke 16.</hi>
               </note> who like a man that ſnorts, and makes a noiſe in his ſleep, is jogged, and pulled, whereas the ſecret ſelf-ſeeker, that ſleeps quietly, is haply let alone by all, and never wakes till hell wakes him; the devill can tempt him without fear. Ieſus Chriſt, indeed who knew the heart beſtowed the moſt of his jogs, and threatnings, and admonitions, upon theſe ſtill and ſlie wretches; and 'tis as obſervable, theſe juſtified themſelves al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and ever had a moſt deadly hatred againſt him.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:112931:27"/>
            <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3. Our great eagerneſſe in ſelf proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> Per mare paupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riem ſugiens, per ſaxa, per ignes.</note> Wee are infinitely <hi>propenſe and eager to do, and in doing any thing for ſelf. Lovers of their own ſelves are particularly mentioned,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. If our own houſes bee burning, our own cauſe a pleading, our own children a dying, our own bargains a driving, how earneſt are we in ſutable affections? Here 'tis true, <hi>quicquid agimus valde agimus;</hi> vehement we are in ſuch proſecutions. The Apoſtle ſpeaks of ſome, that <hi>will be</hi> rich; and the Prophet of ſome, that lie down late, and riſe up early, and eat the bread of anxiety; and the Apoſtle of thoſe, that loved pleaſures more by farre then God; wee read of ſome, that load themſelves with thick clay, and of others, that wearied themſelves in the abundance of their way, when they were in theſe proſecutions for ſelf; in which no bounds of health, prudence, commands, friendſhip, relations, place, promiſe, religion, Scripture, can keep them in; as we ſee in <hi>Balaam</hi> and <hi>Iudas,</hi> the <hi>idolaters of Epheſus, Gebezi;</hi> were not all theſe like a company of ſwift <hi>Dromedaries,</hi> traverſing the wayes of ſelf? when in performance of any thing <hi>for God,</hi> how <hi>dull</hi> are we? when for <hi>ſelf,</hi> how <hi>nimble?</hi> how hearty in <hi>begging our daily bread? how faint in deſiring Gods kingdom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may come?</hi> wee can more eaſily give our <hi>bloud</hi> for <hi>earth,</hi> then our <hi>breath</hi> for <hi>heaven;</hi> when we are about any thing for God, we do it but as it were fainedly, and faintly, wee <hi>under-do it;</hi> but 'tis the hardeſt thing in the world, <hi>when we do any thing for ſelf, not to over-do it:</hi> This is tht common cauſe of all the ſury, and impetuouſneſſe in the world; take away <hi>meum</hi> and <hi>tuum,</hi> mine and thine, and all will fall to the ground;</p>
            <p>There's the firſt diſſwaſive conſideration, from ſeeking theſe things, in regard of the principle, or ground, upon which we are ſo eager in ſeeking them, <hi>viz. theſe being our own;</hi> which argues,</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1 Tim. 6.9.</hi> Ferventiſſimi in terrenis, frigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſimi in coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtbus. Praecep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o non eſt opus ut ſe qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>que diligat, quoniam id quod ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mus &amp; id quod infra nos eſt inconcuſſa na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae lege diligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. <hi>Ambr.</hi> It a afflcicha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ceibus cultum deae re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraturi. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Omnia quae hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribilia audis, ſervire, mori ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piata &amp; ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cta ſunt amori. <hi>Nier.</hi> Tu niſi ſingeres ſic ageres. Otiamur in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus laborandum, laboramus in quibus o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iandion</note> Deceitfulneſſe to our ſelves in ſeeking.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2. Main diſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The things of Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf are neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth, 1 Cor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.22. R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. 16.17. Phil. 3.18. 1. Inſincerity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f aimes.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. quo plus nos qu. in virtu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e erigimus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o in gloriae inanis ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veam proſundius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ademus. <hi>Greg.</hi> Gentes ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt ſub nomine Chriſti. <hi>Tert.</hi> Chriſtian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men adjudicium, non ad remed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um <hi>Aug. Mat. 7.23.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Deus non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it obſequiorum ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciem ſed affectus puritatem. <hi>Amb. in 9. Luc.</hi> Divina judi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia meritum juſti ex mentis habitu, non ex actionum eventu metiuntur. <hi>Id.</hi> Cum perverſa intentione ſi quid vel rectum agatur, quamvis coram hominibus ſplendere cer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itur, apud examen tamen interni judicis obſcuratur. <hi>Greg.</hi>
               </note> Vnworthineſſe, and lowneſſe in ſeeking.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Liableneſſe to ſin in ſeeking.</p>
            <p>The ſecond conſideration to diſſwade us from ſeeking our own things, is this; <hi>Whoſe things they are, which the ſeeking our own, will make us neglect,</hi> viz. The things of Ieſus Chriſt. 'Tis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable, that <hi>Paul</hi> commonly greatens offences, by ſhewing
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:112931:28"/>how they reflect upon Ieſus Chriſt: <hi>If any man love not the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, let him be Anathema Maranatha;</hi> So, <hi>They ſerve not the Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> but, &amp;c. So, <hi>They are enemies to the Croſſe of Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> ſo here, <hi>They ſeeke not the things of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Take this ſecond diſſwaſive branch, as comprehending foure weighty diſſwaſions, every one whereof ſhould take us off from ſelf-ſeeking; The things of Ieſus Chriſt will hereby be neglected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>It is a neglect of the things of one who is in pretence our Lord and Maſter, and whoſe things we ſeem to ſeeke,</hi> and ſo it argueth <hi>inſincerity, and rottenneſſe of intention.</hi> A great ſin; never to bee farther from <hi>ſeeking the things of Chriſt,</hi> then when wee are a <hi>ſeeking</hi> them; to make Ieſus Chriſt <hi>onely a cloak and ſhelter</hi> for our covetouſneſſe, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.5. Onely to make a ſhew of ſervice, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.12. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of Diana,</hi> had <hi>dolum</hi> in <hi>idolo,</hi> deceit in their ſervice, <hi>eager for Diana outwardly,</hi> but their great gains lay under their great cries; onely to be a ſervant in ſhew, an <hi>Angel by name, and a drone in nature,</hi> not to ſerve whom they do ſerve; this temper God abhors; this being in the skin a Chriſtian, and in the coar a heathen; this meer outſide complementall Chriſtianity, that bowes to Chriſt, and yet mocks him, as the ſouldiers did, ſhall bee one day found to have had profeſſion for the increaſing of judgement, not for a remedy to wretchedneſſe; The diſcovery of it, will one day more aſhame, then the ſecrecie of it formerly hath pleaſ'd; Chriſt will uncaſe, uncloak all theſe ſervants; hee will publikely pronounce, that for all their fair ſhewes, he never knew them, <hi>Chriſt will plainly profeſſe it. Impudency then will be daſht out of countenance.</hi> When the Sunne ariſeth, the glow-worme that all night gliſtered brightly, ſhines not at all; no more ſhall theſe glow-worms in religion, when Chriſt ſhall appear in <hi>the brightneſſe of his preſence, 'twill then bee evident, that Chriſt never ſought ſuch to ſerve him,</hi> nor ever regarded their perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances; <hi>he ever reſpecting duty,</hi> and meaſuring actions, not from the event, but the affections: The integrity of the ſoul, and the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:112931:28"/>ſingleneſſe of intention, is the ſweet of every ſervice, and ſacrifice which is made thereby, <hi>ſacrificium medullatum,</hi> the onely ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice with marrow, whereas a ſervice without it, is made up of husks, and ſhadowes, it hath, as we uſe to ſay of ſome meats, no heart in it.</p>
            <p>There's the firſt; A neglect of Chriſts things, argues inſincerity of aime.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>It is a neglect of the things of one, who hath ſought our things, and forſook heaven, and the boſome of his Father for us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion in this ſecond conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, it argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ingratitude. Phil. 2.4.5. Luke 19.10.</note> and if we will not forſake trifles for him; it notes <hi>ingratitude, and an uningenuous temper.</hi> Chriſt ſpun out his very bowels, in a way of love to us; and wee ſpin out our ſtrength, and abilities, in ſinfull luſtings, that are indeed his onely enemies. <hi>Chriſt came to ſeeke,</hi> but what? not ours, but us, that which <hi>was loſt;</hi> Shall he ſeek us, and not we him? he ſought us, when vile and wretched, ſhall not we him, that is ſo glorious and deſireable? They can do no more but neglect Chriſt, that never had any comfort or benefit by him; Shall we neglect him, whoſe induſtries were all employed for our good? 'twas the <hi>meat and drink of Chriſt,</hi> to ſeek and ſave poor loſt ſoules; he went about continually doing good.<note place="margin">Pudeat ſub ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nato Capite mem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rum latere delicatum.</note> 
               <hi>Be aſham'd, O Chriſtian, under ſuch a head, that there ſhould bee ſuch a member, ſo unprofitable, unuſefull as thou art: Chriſt was crown'd with thorns for thee, and will nothing ſerve thy turn but a garland of flowers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There's the ſecond.</p>
            <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">3. It argueth infinite folly to to neglect a ſervice, ſo</note> 
               <hi>It is a neglecting of the things of him, all whoſe employments deſerve ſo well at our hands.</hi> Every thing that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſets us about being,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Very honourable.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Honorable.</note> It is greater honour to bee about the <hi>things of Chriſt,</hi> then to be the head of an Empire. <hi>Paul,</hi> when he calls himſelf ſo frequently in his Epiſtles, the <hi>ſervant of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> is compared by <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> to ſome great Prince, who writing to others, in the beginning of his letter,<note place="margin">Philem. 1.</note> aſſumes ſome lofty title, the more to move reſpect in them that ſhould read it. The higheſt honour of <hi>Paul</hi> was to ſtile himſelf <hi>a priſoner of Chriſt;</hi> the deeper in the <hi>things of Chriſt,</hi> the higher in honour: It is obſerved by ſome,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 24.12.</note> when <hi>David</hi> had ſinned in numbring the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:112931:29"/>people, God would not honour him ſo far, as to call him his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant; Goe ſaith God to <hi>Gad,</hi> and tell <hi>David;</hi> (giving him no title) But when <hi>Davids</hi> heart was ſet upon building God an houſe,<note place="margin">2 Sam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> then God bids <hi>Nathan</hi> go and tell <hi>David his ſervant,</hi> &amp;c. It's a great honour, for God to call us, and count us his ſervants. <hi>Moſes</hi> was a Prince <hi>Ieſurum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t. 34.5.</note> and 'twas his higheſt title to bee called, <hi>Moſes the ſervant of the Lord. David</hi> principally delights to be ſtiled ſo,<note place="margin">Pſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Truely I am thy ſervant, I am thy ſervant.</hi> The badge of Chriſt is a badge of trueſt honour; Every ſervice of Chriſt is very honorable, as admiſſion into the preſence of the great King by prayer, praiſe, (the work of Angels) warring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin, and Satan, principalities, and powers, ſaving of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, of ſoules, helping the Spouſe of the King of Kings, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Delightfull.</note> 
               <hi>Every thing that Chriſt ſets us about, is full of ſweetneſſe, and delight:</hi> In his employments, there are ſoul raviſhing joyes. His ſervice is a <hi>Map of heaven,</hi> the place of rejoycers. A Chriſtian hath never any true comfort in the ſervices of any other, and if he have not comfort evermore in theſe, the fault is not in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, but in the manner of his performing them; theſe <hi>own things,</hi> other employments, in which he hath taken too much liberty, and ſenſuall content, commonly damp his joy. When a man ſweats moſt out wardly, he is coldeſt inwardly; that man who laboureth moſt for, and delighteth moſt in outward things, as <hi>honor, wealth,</hi> &amp;c. (the things that abuſed <hi>ſelf</hi> ſeeks) hath leaſt inward heat of heavenly comfort. There's more true peace in weeping with <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> ſuffering for him, in being diſgraced, impoveriſht, nay in dying for the <hi>things of Chriſt,</hi> then there is in all the ſports, and pleaſures of the world. <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſweetens the ſowreſt perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, gives his people joy, and ſweetneſſe out of the fierceſt, and ſtrongeſt Lion; and his very rod like <hi>Ionathans, hath honey at the end of it;</hi> the truth is, <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath ſuckt out the bitterneſſe, and taken away the burdenſomneſſe of the moſt unpleaſing ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and ſervices; he hath laboured, and wee are entred into his labours: Our ſufferings have now but a <hi>quaſi,</hi> an <hi>[as]</hi> as dying, as ſorrowfull,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.9.</note> as chaſtned, &amp;c. The miſery, the painfulneſſe of every ſuffering, is taken away in the death of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Death it ſelf is a ſword,<note place="margin">Gladius retuſus.</note> that hath loſt its edge, having been ſtrucken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:112931:29"/>
               <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as againſt a R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>k.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chryſ hom. ad pop. Antioch.</note> All the woes in the world have left their ſtings in the ſides of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> The common, ordinary, ſtanding employments of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> are even in themſelves re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhments, and comforts to nature, as meekneſſe, patience, temperance, contentation, love, as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> hath excellently obſerved, in his Sermon perſwading to brotherly love: No man, ſaith hee, can pretend, that this command is deſtructive to his health, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The things of Chriſt are ſafe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Safe. Pſal. 91.1, 2, 4, 11.</note> Chriſt will keep us in all his wayes, <hi>as the apple of the eye, as with wings of warmth and ſhelter, as with a ſhield, &amp;c.</hi> There was never any miſcaried in his works, unleſſe for not being full, and through ſincere,<note place="margin">Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch. 2.8.</note> and conſtant in them, they minding <hi>their own things</hi> more then his. A Saint may <hi>commit himſelf to Chriſt in well doing;</hi> How ſafe even outwardly,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.19.</note> when God ſees it ſafeſt for their ſoules, doth he keep them, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing even their carcaſſes, which are but the <hi>cabinets,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Iu medio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aginae.</note> and <hi>caſes</hi> of their ſoules, moſt tenderly from hurt and injury? but how ever, God will keep the ſoul which is more endangered in the ſweeteſt employments of <hi>ſelf,</hi> then in the hardeſt of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">In periculis ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ri. in ſecuris pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>litamur.</note> The keeping of the ſpirit, is the gracious keeping; and often that, even ſees greateſt ſafety in the approach of outward dangers, <hi>mountains full of chariots and horſes of fire;</hi> A <hi>reſerve</hi> of mercy, and love, and ſtrength, drawing neer to ſuſtain it,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.37. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> making it more then a conqueror. The very height of danger ſends a Saint beyond danger, even into the <hi>boſome of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> A dying Saint may ſay to all miſeries, as <hi>Chriſt to the Iews, Whither I go, ye ſhall not come;</hi> 'Tis poſſible indeed, there may in the paſſage be fear, but yet 'tis certaine, there is <hi>ſafety: Safety</hi> though ſickneſſe, ſafety though poverty, though death, &amp;c. A childe of God in greateſt worldly unſafeneſſe, is like a ſhip upon a boyſterous Sea, and driven with a ſtrong winde, but yet ſuch a winde, which is not ſo ſtrong to affright, as it is right ſet, to carry to the Haven;<note place="margin">Matth. 10.28.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt forbids fear.</p>
            <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">4. Advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pſal. 19.</note> 
               <hi>All the things of Chriſt, and his employments are advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous;</hi> None ſhall be loſers by them. Indeed <hi>Chriſts things</hi> ſhould not be ſought onely for reward, but <hi>Chriſt</hi> will not ſuffer them to be ſought without reward; the things of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> like the ſeed that <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſowed, bring forth an hundred-fold, in reſpect of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:112931:30"/>
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> will be beholding to none, they ſhall bee paid to the full: Indeed ſometime he asketh day, but when the day of payment comes, hee infinitely more then countervaileth for deferring; All that wee doe, or ſuffer, in the hardeſt things of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> are not <hi>worthy the glory that shall be revealed.</hi> They can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo much as <hi>ſtir that ballance wherein glory is,</hi> though all the ſufferings and employments in the world were thrown into the other.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.18. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Chriſt takes notice of all the things that are done for him, all are ſet down and regiſtred. In the building the wall, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up the gates of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> all is obſerved, even to the making of barres, and locks for the gates. Every piece of a ſeemingly mean work,<note place="margin">N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. 3.3. Luk. 7.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> is rehearſed by Chriſt. A Saint is like a rich man, that drives a ſecret trade, his dangers and ſlight loſſes are ſeene haply,<note place="margin">Col. 3.3.</note> but his cloſe gain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s are inviſible. <hi>Our life is hid</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> ſweetly) <hi>with Chriſt in God;</hi> Our happineſſe is laid up, and ſecret indeed, but yet <hi>it is,</hi> and is abundant too. For the preſent, ſo far forth as 'tis good for them, Saints ſhall bee rewarded, even in this life; and if it bee not for their good, what reward call you that?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 'tis an angry reward; it would bee a better reward to want it.</p>
            <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">4. Diſſwaſion in the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration. It argues fearleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</note> 
               <hi>The neglecting of the tings of Ieſus Chriſt, is of the things of one, that will one day call us to an account and reckoning,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire at our hands, all thoſe neglects of himſelf, and wayes, and ſervants, and cauſe; ſo it argues <hi>regardleſneſſe of account,</hi> fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe of reckoning. There's not one ſervant but 'twill be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of him, what he hath done; he will be called to a recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; and therefore <hi>Paul</hi> chargeth <hi>Timothy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.1.</note> to look well to the things of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> for he tells him, there will come a reckoning, an anſwering day: elſewhere the Apoſtle tells us of an account that muſt be made of our looking after the things of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> You may bribe your own conſciences, but never him, that is to call you to the account;<note place="margin">Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mus, ſed non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tinguim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> people may be ſilent of it, and forget it themſelves, but they cannot make Chriſt forget it. Seek the things of Chriſt in his Church, in his Cauſe, in his Word, in his Servants; if ever you would have him regard you hereafter, regard him here. Be a ſhield to Chriſts cauſe now, if thou wouldſt have him to be a ſhield to thee hereafter. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Oneſiphorus</hi> ſought him out diligently,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.17, 18</note> and refreſhed him, even in his chaines,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:112931:30"/>and we ſee what follows, even a prayer, that he may finde mercy from Chriſt in that day of account, ſince hee had ſought theſe things of Chriſt before.</p>
            <p>And thus I have done with the firſt generall part of the Text, the nature of the offence. 2. The generality of the offenders follows.</p>
            <p>The ſecond generall head in the Text, is the generality of the offenders. <hi>All</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) ſeek, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>An expreſſion, which I conceive, comprehends a threefold re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, or looks with a threefold Aſpect;</p>
            <p n="1">1. Vpon <hi>Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Vpon <hi>Timothy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Vpon the generality of whom the Apoſtle here complains that they ſought their own things.</p>
            <p>I ſhall name all the three reſpects.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As it hath reference to <hi>Paul,</hi> it notes two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sorrowfull reſenting of the neglect of the Church, even as if every one had forſaken it, and not one left to own it, and the things of Chriſt. A gracious perſon, deeply and ſadly layes to heart the neglect of the things of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Wee finde (as I ſaid before) Saint <hi>Paul</hi> once <hi>weeping in this Epiſtle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.18.</note> but 'twas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of ſome that were not friends to Ieſus Chriſt.<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Fr. Bacons</hi> Nat. Hiſt.</note> When two ſtrings of an Inſtrument are tuned one to the other, if the one be ſtruck upon, and ſtir'd, the other will move and tremble alſo. A Saints ſoul is harmoniouſly conſenting in its affections to Chriſt; and if he ſuffer and be ſtruck, a Saint will tremble, and bee moved likewiſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.3.</note> In reference to <hi>Paul,</hi> it notes courage in reproving zeale in oppoſing a ſpreading fault; <hi>Paul</hi> dares ſpeak even againſt all, if all will neglect Chriſt: A gracious heart will ſtand for Ieſus Chriſt, in the midſt even of a prevailing number that oppoſe him; the multitude and generality of reſiſters hee meets withall, will not, muſt not, make him deſiſt; And therefore hence we may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a probable mark of a Chriſtians, or a Miniſters ſincerity; doe they oppoſe the ſpreading prevailing ſinnes of the time wherein they live? It's ordinary to ſee and hear men cry down ſinnes that are put down, and diſcountenanced to their hand, that perhaps, have few or none to plead for them; but the ſinnes of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:112931:31"/>the age and place, as ſuppoſe it be erroneouſneſſe in judgement, or contempt of the publique Ordinances, reviling the Saints, ſlightneſſe in religion, &amp;c. theſe ſinnes that are in faſhion, and are prevailing, require a courage and a faithfulneſſe, like to <hi>Pauls</hi> to deal with them.</p>
            <p>There's the firſt reſpect in the word <hi>[All,] viz.</hi> to <hi>Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond reſpect of this word <hi>[All,]</hi> is as it concerns <hi>Timothy,</hi> whoſe graces of zeal, and integrity the Apoſtle doth clearly here beautifie and adorne by that <hi>foyl</hi> of <hi>ſelf-ſeeking</hi> in others. In the foregoing verſe he had commended <hi>Timothy</hi> for his uprightneſſe and zeal for the Churches good, here hee ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies that commendation, from ſetting down how oppoſite the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality was to him; he was for <hi>the things of Chriſt,</hi> though the moſt were againſt him; And thus it notes, The true commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>That Chriſtians piety and zeal <hi>for Chriſt,</hi> is <hi>moſt</hi> highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, which holds up,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.15. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in times and places, when, and where Chriſt is neglected. The darkneſſe of the night makes the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, or the ſtar, the more bright and ſhining:</p>
            <p>There's the ſecond.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As this word <hi>[all]</hi> here refers to the generality; who were Brethren, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ellow-labourers, and profeſſors, even toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Timothy;</hi> it notes,</p>
            <p>Diſcovery (by difficulties) even of the faireſt pretenders to the things of Ieſus Chriſt: It's a rare thing, even among great numbers of Chriſts ſeeming friends, to find thoſe that in ſtraights will cleave to him: Who is it almoſt that forſakes him not, and flies, when following him, is followed with dangers? Very few that continue with Chriſt in <hi>an hour of temptation.</hi> Chriſtians for the moſt part, take up profeſſion of Religion, as ſome people go to Sea, upon pleaſure and recreation; when the weather grows ſtormy, they preſently think of comming back again. Vnſound fruit will hang on the tree, in a fair Sun-ſhining-day, but in a boyſterous windy day, it ſoone falls off. Outward troubles will overcome a meerely viſible and outſide profeſſor, but they cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>each the ſoul truely implanted into Chriſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
